<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iter boreale with large additions of several other poems : being an exact collection of all hitherto extant : never before published together / the author R. Wild.</title>
            <author>Wild, Robert, 1609-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12380010</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12380010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 649:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iter boreale with large additions of several other poems : being an exact collection of all hitherto extant : never before published together / the author R. Wild.</title>
                  <author>Wild, Robert, 1609-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-120 [i.e. 122], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The recantation of a penitent Proteus" and "The fair quarrel" each has special title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Iter Boreale. With large Additions of ſeveral other POEMS BEING An EXACT COLLECTION of all hitherto Extant.</p>
            <p>Never before Publiſhed together.</p>
            <p>The Author <hi>R. Wild,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Bookſellers in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> MDCLXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>House of Hanover bookplate</figDesc>
                  <p>MVNIFICENTIA REGIA. 1715.</p>
                  <p>GEORGIVS D. G. MAG. BR. FR. ET HIB. REX F. D.</p>
                  <byline>J. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Sculp</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60727:2"/>
               <head>Iter Boreale. Attempting ſomthing upon the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful and Matchleſs March of the LORD GENERAL George Monck, From SCOTLAND to LONDON, in the Winter, 1659.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>THe day is broke! <hi>Melpomene,</hi> be gone;</l>
                  <l>Hag of my Fancy, let me now alone:</l>
                  <l>Night-mare my Soul no more; Go take thy flight</l>
                  <l>Where Traitors Ghoſts keep an eternal night;</l>
                  <l>Flee to Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> and bear thy part</l>
                  <l>With the black fowl that tears <hi>Prometheus</hi> heart</l>
                  <l>For his bold Sacriledg: Go fetch the groans</l>
                  <l>Of defunct Tyrants, with them croke thy Tones;</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60727:3"/>
                  <l>Go ſee <hi>Alecto</hi> with her flaming whip,</l>
                  <l>How ſhe fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks <hi>Nol,</hi> and makes old <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> skip:</l>
                  <l>Go make thy ſelf away,—Thou ſhalt no more</l>
                  <l>Choak up my Stand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh with the blood and gore</l>
                  <l>Of Engliſh Tragedies: I now will chuſe</l>
                  <l>The merrieſt of the nine to be my Muſe:</l>
                  <l>And come what will, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le scribble once again:</l>
                  <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sword hath cut the nobler Vein</l>
                  <l>Of racy Poetry. Our ſmall-drink-times</l>
                  <l>Muſt be contented, and take up with Rhimes.</l>
                  <l>They'r ſorry toyes from a poor Levites pack,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Living and Aſſeſments drink no Sack.</l>
                  <l>The Subject will excuſe the Verſe (I trow)</l>
                  <l>The Ven ſon's fat, although the cruſt be dough.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>I He who whileom ſate and ſung in Cage</l>
                  <l>My Kings and Countries Ruines by the rage</l>
                  <l>Of a rebellious Rout; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o weeping ſaw</l>
                  <l>Three goodly Kingdoms (drunk with fury) draw</l>
                  <l>And ſheath their Swords (like three engaged bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</l>
                  <l>In one anothers ſides, ripping their Mothers</l>
                  <l>Belly, and tearing out her bleeding heart;</l>
                  <l>Then jealous that their Father fain would part</l>
                  <l>Their bloody fray, and let them fight no more,</l>
                  <l>Fell foul on Him, and ſlew Him at His dore.</l>
                  <l>I that have only dar'd to whiſper Verſes,</l>
                  <l>And drop a tear (by ſtealth) on loyal Hearſes;</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60727:3"/>
                  <l>I that enraged at the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Rump,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had gnaw'd my Gooſe-quill to the very ſtump,</l>
                  <l>And flung that in the Fire, no more to write,</l>
                  <l>But to ſit down poor <hi>Britains Heraclite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now ſing the triumphs of the Men of War,</l>
                  <l>The Glorious Rayes of the bright Northern Star,</l>
                  <l>Created for the nonce by Heaven to bring</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men of three Nations to their King:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MONCK!</hi> the great <hi>Monck!</hi> that ſyllable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhines</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plantagenet's</hi> bright Name, or <hi>Conſtantine's.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'T was at His Riſing that <hi>Our Day</hi> begun,</l>
                  <l>Be he the <hi>Morning Star</hi> to <hi>CHARLES</hi> our <hi>Sun.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He took Rebellion rampant, by the throat,</l>
                  <l>And made the Canting <hi>Quaker</hi> change his Note;</l>
                  <l>His hand it was that wrote, (we ſaw no more)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exit Tyrannus</hi> over <hi>Lamberts</hi> dore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like to ſome ſubtle Lightning, ſo His Words</l>
                  <l>Diſſolved in their Scabbards Rebels Swords.</l>
                  <l>He with ſucceſs the <hi>Soveraign</hi> skill hath found</l>
                  <l>To dreſs the Weapon, and to heal the Wound.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>George,</hi> and his Boyes (as Spirits do, they ſay)</l>
                  <l>Only by walking, ſcare our Foes away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>OLd <hi>Holofernes</hi> was no ſooner laid,</l>
                  <l>Before the Idols Funeral Pomp was paid,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60727:4"/>
                  <l>(Nor ſhall a penny ere be paid for me;</l>
                  <l>Let fools that truſted his true Mourners be.)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the Fourth, juſt peeping out of Squire,</l>
                  <l>No fault ſo much, as th'old one was his Sire;</l>
                  <l>For men believ'd,—though all went in his Name,</l>
                  <l>Hee'd be but Tenant till the Landlord came:</l>
                  <l>When on a ſudden (all amaz'd) we found</l>
                  <l>The ſeven years <hi>Babel</hi> tumbled to the ground;</l>
                  <l>And he, poor heart, (thanks to his cunning Kin)</l>
                  <l>Was ſoon in <hi>Querpo</hi> honeſt <hi>Dick</hi> agen.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exit Protector.</hi>—What comes next? I trow,</l>
                  <l>Let the State-Huntſmen beat again.—So-ho,</l>
                  <l>Cries <hi>Lambert,</hi> Maſter of the Hounds,—Here ſits</l>
                  <l>That luſty Puſs, <hi>The Good Old Cauſe,—whoſe wits</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shew'd <hi>Oliver</hi> ſuch ſport; That, that (cries <hi>Vane)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lets put her up, and run her once again:</l>
                  <l>She'l lead our Dogs and Followers up and down,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we match Families, and take the Crown.</l>
                  <l>Enter th'old Members: 'T was the Month of <hi>May</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe Maggots in the <hi>Rump</hi> began to play:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wallingford</hi> Anglers (though they ſtunk) yet thought</l>
                  <l>They would make baits, by which Fiſh might be caught;</l>
                  <l>And ſo it prov'd, they ſoon by taxes made</l>
                  <l>More money than the <hi>Holland</hi> Fiſhing Trade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>NOw broke in <hi>Egypts</hi> Plagues (all in a day)</l>
                  <l>And one more worſe than theirs,—We muſt not pray</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60727:4"/>
                  <l>To be deliver'd:—Their ſcab'd folks were free</l>
                  <l>To ſcratch where it did itch;—So might not we.</l>
                  <l>That Meteor <hi>Cromwel,</hi> though he ſcar'd, gave light;</l>
                  <l>But we were now cover'd with horrid night:</l>
                  <l>Our Magiſtracy was (like <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod)</l>
                  <l>Turn'd to a Serpent by the angry God.</l>
                  <l>Poor Citizens, when Trading would not do,</l>
                  <l>Made brick without ſtraw, and were blaſted too:</l>
                  <l>Struck with the botch of Taxes and Exciſe;</l>
                  <l>Servants <hi>(our very duſt)</hi> were turn'd to <hi>Lice;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It was but turning Souldiers, and they need</l>
                  <l>Not work at all, but on their Maſters feed.</l>
                  <l>Strange Catterpillars are our pleaſant things;</l>
                  <l>And Frogs croakt in the Chambers of our Kings:</l>
                  <l>Black bloody veins did in the <hi>Rump</hi> prevail,</l>
                  <l>Like the Philiſtims Emrods in the Tayle.</l>
                  <l>Lightning, Hall, Fire, and Thunder <hi>Egypt</hi> had,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>England</hi> Guns, Shot, Powder, (thats as bad.)</l>
                  <l>And that Sea-Monſter <hi>Lawſon</hi> (if withſtood)</l>
                  <l>Threatned to turn our Rivers into Blood.</l>
                  <l>And (Plague of all theſe Plagues) all theſe Plagues fell</l>
                  <l>Not on an <hi>Egypt,</hi> but our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>SIck (as her heart can hold) the Nation lies,</l>
                  <l>Filling each corner with her hideous cries:</l>
                  <l>Somtimes Rage (like a burning Fever) hearts,</l>
                  <l>Anon Deſpair brings cold and clammy Sweats;</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60727:5"/>
                  <l>She cannot ſleep: or if ſhe doth ſhe dreams</l>
                  <l>Of Rapes, Thefts, Burnings, Blood, and direful theams;</l>
                  <l>Toſſes from ſide to ſide, then by and by</l>
                  <l>Her feet are laid there where the head did lie:</l>
                  <l>None can come to her but bold Empericks,</l>
                  <l>Who never meant to cure her but try tricks:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe very <hi>Doctors</hi> who ſhould give her eaſe,</l>
                  <l>(God help the <hi>Patient)</hi> was her worſt diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Italian</hi> Mountebank <hi>Vane</hi> tells her ſure</l>
                  <l>Jeſuits Powder will effect the Cure.</l>
                  <l>If grief but makes her ſwell, <hi>Martin</hi> and <hi>Nevil</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conclude it is a ſpice of the Kings-Evil.</l>
                  <l>Bleed her again, another cries;—And <hi>Scot</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Saith he could cure her, if 'twas—you know what:</l>
                  <l>But giddy <hi>Harrington</hi> a whimſey found,</l>
                  <l>To make her head (like to his brains) run round:</l>
                  <l>Her old and wiſe Phyſitians, who before</l>
                  <l>Had well nigh cur'd her, came again to th' dore,</l>
                  <l>But were kept out, which made her cry the more,</l>
                  <l>Help, help, <hi>(dear Children)</hi> Oh! ſome pity take</l>
                  <l>On her who bore you! help for mercy ſake!</l>
                  <l>Oh heart! Oh head! Oh back! Oh bones! I feel</l>
                  <l>They've poyſon'd me with giving too much ſteel:</l>
                  <l>Oh give me that for which I long and cry!</l>
                  <l>Somthing that's <hi>Soveraign,</hi> or elſe I dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60727:5"/>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>KInd <hi>Cheſhire</hi> heard;—And like ſome ſon that ſtood</l>
                  <l>Upon the Bank, ſtraight jump'd into the <hi>flood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Flings out his arms, &amp; ſtrikes ſom ſtrokes to ſivim</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Booth</hi> ventur'd firſt, and <hi>Middleton</hi> with him;</l>
                  <l>Stout <hi>Mackworth, Egerton,</hi> and thouſands more,</l>
                  <l>Threw themſelves in, and left the ſafer ſhore;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maſſey</hi> (that famous Diver) and bold <hi>Brown</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Forſook his Wharf,—reſolving all to drown,</l>
                  <l>Or ſave a ſinking Kingdom:—But, O ſad!</l>
                  <l>Fearing to loſe her prey, the Sea grew mad,</l>
                  <l>Rais'd all her billows, and reſolv'd her waves,</l>
                  <l>Should quickly be the bold Adventurers graves.</l>
                  <l>Out Marches <hi>Lambert,</hi> like an Eaſtern Wind,</l>
                  <l>And with him all the mighty waters joyn'd.</l>
                  <l>The Loyal Swimmers bore up heads and breaſts,</l>
                  <l>Scorning to think of Life or Intereſts;</l>
                  <l>They ply'd their Arms and Thighs, but all in vain;</l>
                  <l>The furious Main beat them to ſhore again;</l>
                  <l>At which the floating Iſland (looking back,</l>
                  <l>Spying her loyal Lovers gone to wrack)</l>
                  <l>Shriekt lowder then before,—and thus ſhe cries,</l>
                  <l>"Can you be angry heavens, and frowning skies,</l>
                  <l>"Thus countenance rebellious Mutineers,</l>
                  <l>"Who, if they durſt, would be about your ears?</l>
                  <l>"That I ſhould ſink, with Juſtice may accord,</l>
                  <l>"Who let my Pilot be thrown over-board;</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60727:6"/>
                  <l>"Yet 'twas not I (ye righteous Heavens do know)</l>
                  <l>"The Soldiers in me needs would have it ſo:</l>
                  <l>"And thoſe who conjur'd up theſe ſtorms them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</l>
                  <l>"And firſt engag'd me 'mongſt theſe Rocks and Shelves</l>
                  <l>"Guilty of all my wo, have rais'd this weather,</l>
                  <l>"Fearing to come to Land, and chuſing rather</l>
                  <l>"To ſink me with themſelves,—O ceaſe to frown</l>
                  <l>"In tears (juſt Heavens!) behold! my ſelf I drown:</l>
                  <l>"Let not theſe proud waves do't: Prevent my fears,</l>
                  <l>"And let them fall together by the ears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>HEav'n heard, and ſtruck th'inſulting army mad</l>
                  <l>Drunk with their <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Triumphs, ſtraight they had</l>
                  <l>New Lights appear'd, and new Reſolves they take,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Single Perſon</hi> once again to make.</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall be he? Oh! <hi>Lambert,</hi> without rub,</l>
                  <l>The fitteſt Devil to be <hi>Belzebub.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He, the fierce Fiend, caſt out o'th' Houſe before,</l>
                  <l>Return'd, and threw the Houſe now out of door:</l>
                  <l>A Legion then he rais'd of Armed Sprights,</l>
                  <l>Elves, Goblins, Faires, Quakers, and new Lights,</l>
                  <l>To be his under Devils, with this reſt</l>
                  <l>He Soul and Body (Church and State) poſſeſt:</l>
                  <l>Who tho they fil'd all countries, towns, and rooms</l>
                  <l>Yet (like that Fiend that did frequent the Tombs)</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60727:6"/>
                  <l>Churches, and Sacred Grounds they haunted moſt,</l>
                  <l>No Chappel was at eaſe from ſome ſuch Ghoſt.</l>
                  <l>The Prieſts ordain'd to exerciſe thoſe Elves,</l>
                  <l>Were voted Devils, and caſt out themſelves:</l>
                  <l>Bible, or Alchoran, all's one to them,</l>
                  <l>Religion ſerves but for a ſtratagem:</l>
                  <l>The holy Charms theſe Adders did not heed,</l>
                  <l>Churches themſelves did Sanctuary need.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>THe Churches Patrimony and rich Store,</l>
                  <l>Alas! was ſwallow'd many years before:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deans</hi> we ſed upon before,</l>
                  <l>They were the <hi>Ribs</hi> and <hi>Surloyns</hi> of the Whore:</l>
                  <l>Now let her <hi>Legs</hi> (the <hi>Prieſts</hi> go to the Pot,</l>
                  <l>(They have the Pope's eye in them) ſpare them not:</l>
                  <l>We have fat Benefices yet to eat,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Bell,</hi> and our <hi>Dragon-</hi>Army muſt have meat:)</l>
                  <l>Let us devour her Limb-meal, great and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Tythe Calves, Geeſe, Pigs, the Petitoes and all:</l>
                  <l>A Vicaridg in Sippets, though it be</l>
                  <l>But ſmall, will ſerve a ſqueamiſh Sectary.</l>
                  <l>Though Univerſities we can't endure,</l>
                  <l>There's no falſe Latine in their Lands (be ſure.)</l>
                  <l>Give <hi>Oxford</hi> to our Horſe, and let the Foot</l>
                  <l>Take <hi>Cambridge</hi> for their booty, and fall too't.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> ile have (cries <hi>Vane;) Disbrow</hi> ſwops</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Trinity; Kings</hi> is for <hi>Berry</hi>'s chops;</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60727:7"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kelſey,</hi> take <hi>Corpus Chriſti; All-Souls, Packer;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Grave <hi>Creed, St. Johns; New Colledg</hi> leave to <hi>Hacker;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fleetwood</hi> cries, <hi>Weeping Maudlin</hi> ſhall be mine,</l>
                  <l>Her tears Ile drink inſtead of <hi>Muſcadine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſmaller <hi>Halls</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> ſcarce are big</l>
                  <l>Enough to make one diſh for <hi>Haſilrig;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We muſt be ſure to ſtop his mouth, though wide,</l>
                  <l>Elſe all our fat will be i'th fire (they cry'd:</l>
                  <l>And when we have done theſe, we'l not be quiet,</l>
                  <l>Lordſhips and Landlords Rents ſhall be our diet.</l>
                  <l>Thus talk'd this jolly crew, but ſtill mine 'Hoſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lambert</hi> reſolves that he will rule the Roſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>BUt hark! Methinks I hear old <hi>Boreas</hi> blow;</l>
                  <l>What mean the north-winds that they bluſter ſo?</l>
                  <l>More ſtorms from that black nook? Forbear (bold <hi>Scot</hi>!)</l>
                  <l>Let not <hi>Dunbar</hi> and <hi>Worc'ſter</hi> be forgot:</l>
                  <l>What? would you chaffer w'us for one <hi>Charls</hi> more</l>
                  <l>The price of Kings is fal'n, give the Trade o're.</l>
                  <l>And is the price of Kings and Kingdoms too,</l>
                  <l>Of Laws, lives, oaths, ſouls, grown ſo low with you?</l>
                  <l>Perfidious Hypocrites! Monſters of Men!</l>
                  <l>(Cries the good <hi>Monck)</hi> we'l raiſe their price agen</l>
                  <l>Heaven ſaid <hi>Amen,</hi> and breath'd upon that Spark;</l>
                  <l>That Spark (preſerv'd alive i'th cold and dark)</l>
                  <l>Firſt kindled and enflam'd the Britiſh Iſle,</l>
                  <l>And turn'd it all to Bonefires in a while:</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60727:7"/>
                  <l>He and his fewel was ſo ſmall, no doubt,</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Lambert</hi> thought to tread or piſs them out.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>George</hi> was wary;—His cauſe did require</l>
                  <l>A Pillar of a Cloud as well as Fire:</l>
                  <l>'Twas not his ſafeſt courſe to flame, but ſmoak;</l>
                  <l>His enemies he will not burn but choak;</l>
                  <l>Small Fires muſt not blaze out, leſt by their light</l>
                  <l>They ſhew their weakneſs, and their foes invite;</l>
                  <l>But Furnaces the ſtouteſt Metals melt,</l>
                  <l>(And ſo did he) by fire not ſeen, but felt;</l>
                  <l>Dark-lanthorn Language, and his peep-bo-play,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Will-E-Wiſpt Lambert's</hi> new Lights out o'th way.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>George</hi> &amp; his boys, thoſe thouſands (ô ſtrang thing)</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Snipes</hi> and <hi>Woodcocks</hi> took by Lowbelling.</l>
                  <l>His few Scotch-Coal kindled with Engliſh Fire</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Lamberts</hi> great <hi>Nowcaſtle</hi> heaps expire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SCotland</hi> (though poor and peeviſh) was content</l>
                  <l>To keep the Peace, and (O rare!) money lent;</l>
                  <l>But yet the bleſſing of their Kirk was more;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>George</hi> had that too, and with this ſlender ſtore</l>
                  <l>He and his Mirmidons advance:—Kind Heaven</l>
                  <l>Prepar'd a Froſt to make their March more eaven</l>
                  <l>Eaſy and ſafe; it may be ſaid, That year</l>
                  <l>Of th' High-ways Heaven it ſelf was Overſeer,</l>
                  <l>And made-<hi>November</hi> ground as hard as <hi>May;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>White as their Innocence, ſo was their Way:</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60727:8"/>
                  <l>The Clouds came down in Feather-beds, to greet</l>
                  <l>Him and his Army, and to kiſs their feet.</l>
                  <l>The froſt and foes both came and went together,</l>
                  <l>Both thaw'd away, &amp; vaniſh'd God knows whither.</l>
                  <l>Whole Countries crowded in to ſee this friend,</l>
                  <l>Ready to caſt their bodies down to mend</l>
                  <l>His Road to <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and ſtill they ſhout,</l>
                  <l>Lay hold of th' <hi>Rump,</hi> and pull the <hi>Monſter</hi> out:</l>
                  <l>A new one, or a whole one <hi>(Good my Lord)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to this cry the Iſland did accord,</l>
                  <l>The Eccho of the Iriſh hollow ground</l>
                  <l>Heard <hi>England,</hi> and her language did rebound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <l>PReſto-<hi>Jack Lambert,</hi> and his Sprights are gone</l>
                  <l>To dance a Jig with's brother <hi>Oberon:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>George</hi> made him, and his Cut-throats of our lives,</l>
                  <l>Swallow their ſwords as Juglers do their Knives.</l>
                  <l>And Carter <hi>Disborough</hi> to wiſh in vain,</l>
                  <l>He now were Waggoner to <hi>Charls</hi> his Wain.</l>
                  <l>The Conqueror is now come into th' South,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe warm Air is made hot by every mouth;</l>
                  <l>Breathing his welcome, and in ſpite of <hi>Scot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Crying—<hi>The whole Child</hi> (Sir) <hi>divide it not:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Rump begins to ſtink; Alas! (cry they)</l>
                  <l>W'have rais'd a Devil which we cannot lay.</l>
                  <l>I like him not—His Belly is ſo big,</l>
                  <l>There's a King in't, cryes furious <hi>Haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lrig,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60727:8"/>
                  <l>Let's bribe Him (they cry all) Carve him a ſhare</l>
                  <l>Of our ſtoln Veniſon.—Varlets forbear,</l>
                  <l>In vain you put your Lime twigs to his Hands</l>
                  <l>George Monck <hi>is for the King, not for his Lands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When fair means would not do, next foul they try,</l>
                  <l>Vote him the City Scavenger, (they cry)</l>
                  <l>Send him to fcowr their Streets.—Well, let it be;</l>
                  <l>Your Rumpſhip wants a fcowring too, (thinks he)</l>
                  <l>That foul houſe where your Worſhips many year</l>
                  <l>Have laid your Tail, ſure wants a Scavenger:</l>
                  <l>I ſmell your Fizzle, though it make no Crack,</l>
                  <l>You'ld mount me on the Cities galled Back,</l>
                  <l>In hope ſhe'll caſt her Rider: If I muſt</l>
                  <l>Upon ſome Office in the Town be thruſt,</l>
                  <l>I'le be their Sword-bearer,—and to their Dagger</l>
                  <l>I'le joyn my Sword:—Nay, <hi>(good Rump)</hi> do not ſwagger,</l>
                  <l>The City feaſts me, and as ſure as Gun)</l>
                  <l>I'le mend all <hi>Englands</hi> Commons e're I've done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <l>ANd ſo he did: One morning next his heart</l>
                  <l>He goes to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and play'd his part;</l>
                  <l>He vampt their boots (which <hi>Hewſon</hi> ne'r could do)</l>
                  <l>With better leather, made them g'upright too.</l>
                  <l>The Reſtor'd Members <hi>(Cato</hi>-like, no doubt)</l>
                  <l>Did only enter that They might go out;</l>
                  <l>They did not mean within thoſe Walls to dwell,</l>
                  <l>Nor did they like their Company ſo well:</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60727:9"/>
                  <l>Yet Heav'n ſo bleſt them, that in three weeks ſpace</l>
                  <l>They gave both Church and State a better face;</l>
                  <l>They gave <hi>Boath, Maſſy, Brown,</hi> ſome kinder lots;</l>
                  <l>The laſt years Traytors, this years Patriots:</l>
                  <l>The Churches poor Remainder they made good,</l>
                  <l>And waſh'd the Nations Hands of Royal Blood;</l>
                  <l>And that a Parliament (they did deviſe)</l>
                  <l>From its own aſhes <hi>(Phaenix</hi>-like) might riſe;</l>
                  <l>This done, By <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Deed</hi> that might not fail,</l>
                  <l>They paſt a Fine, and ſo cut off <hi>th' Entail.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <l>LEt the Bells ring theſe Changes now from <hi>Bow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Down to the Country Candleſticks below;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ringers,</hi> hands off; The Bells themſelves will dance</l>
                  <l>In memory of their own deliverance.</l>
                  <l>Had not <hi>George</hi> ſhew'd his Metal, and ſaid Nay,</l>
                  <l>Each Sectary had born the Bell away:</l>
                  <l>Down with them all, they'r Chriſtned (cry'd that Crew)</l>
                  <l>Tye up their Clappers, and the Parſons too;</l>
                  <l>Turn them to Guns, or ſell them to the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay, hold, (quoth <hi>George)</hi> my Maſters, that's too much</l>
                  <l>You will not leap o're Steeples thus, I hope</l>
                  <l>I'le ſave the Bells, but you may take the Rope.</l>
                  <l>Thus lay <hi>Religion</hi> panting for her life,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Iſaac,</hi> bound under the bloody knife;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>George</hi> held the falling Weapon, ſav'd the Lamb:</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Lambert</hi> (in the Briars) be the <hi>Ram.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60727:9"/>
                  <l>So lay the Royal Virgin (as 'tis told)</l>
                  <l>When brave S. <hi>George</hi> redeem'd her life, of old.</l>
                  <l>Oh that the Knaves that have conſum'd our Land,</l>
                  <l>Had but permitted Wood enough to ſtand</l>
                  <l>To be his Bonfires;—Wee'd burn every ſtem,</l>
                  <l>And leave no more but Gallow-trees for them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <l>MArch on, <hi>Great Heroe!</hi> as thou haſt begun,</l>
                  <l>And crown our <hi>Happineſs</hi> before th'aſt done</l>
                  <l>We have another <hi>CHARLES</hi> to fetch from <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be thou the <hi>GEORGE</hi> to bring him back again:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhalt thou be (what was deny'd that Knight)</l>
                  <l>Thy Princes, and the Peoples Favorite.</l>
                  <l>There is no danger of the Winds at all,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs together by the Ears they fall,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall the honour have to waft a King:</l>
                  <l>And they who gain it, while they work ſhall ſing.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee how thoſe Triumphant Gales,</l>
                  <l>Proud of the great Enployment, ſwell the Sails:</l>
                  <l>The joyful Ship ſhall dance, the Sea ſhall laugh,</l>
                  <l>And loyal Fiſh their Maſters health ſhall quaff:</l>
                  <l>See how the <hi>Dolphins</hi> croud and thruſt their large</l>
                  <l>And ſcaly ſhoulders, to aſſiſt the Barge;</l>
                  <l>The peaceful Kingfiſhers are met together</l>
                  <l>About the Decks and propheſie calm weather;</l>
                  <l>Poor Crabs and Lobſters are gone down to creep,</l>
                  <l>And ſearch for Pearls and Jewels in the deep;</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60727:10"/>
                  <l>And when they have the booty,—crawl before,</l>
                  <l>And leave them for his welcome to the Shore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <l>ME-thinks I ſee how throngs of people ſtand</l>
                  <l>Scarce patient till the Veſſel come to Land,</l>
                  <l>Ready to leap in, and if need require,</l>
                  <l>With Tears of Joy, to make the waters higher.</l>
                  <l>But what will <hi>London</hi> do? I doubt Old <hi>Paul</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With bowing to his Soveraign will fall,</l>
                  <l>The Royal Lyons from the Tower ſhall roar,</l>
                  <l>And though they ſee him not, yet ſhall adore:</l>
                  <l>The Conduits will be raviſh'd, and combine</l>
                  <l>To turn their very water into Wine:</l>
                  <l>And for the Citizens, I only pray</l>
                  <l>They may not over-joy'd all die that day:</l>
                  <l>May we all live more loyal and more true,</l>
                  <l>To give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> and to God their due.</l>
                  <l>Wee'l make his Fathers Tomb with tears to ſwim</l>
                  <l>And for the Son we'll ſhed our blood for him.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> her penitential Song ſhall ſing,</l>
                  <l>And take heed how ſhe quarrels with her King.</l>
                  <l>If for our ſins—our Prince ſhall be miſled,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l bite our nails, rather than ſcratch our <hi>head.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60727:10"/>
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <l>ONe Engliſh <hi>George</hi> out-weighs alone (by odds)</l>
                  <l>A whole Committee of the Heathens Gods;</l>
                  <l>Pronounce but <hi>Monck,</hi> and (it is all his due)</l>
                  <l>He is our <hi>Mercury, Mars,</hi> and <hi>Neptune</hi> too.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Monck</hi> (what great <hi>Xerxes</hi> could not) prov'd the man</l>
                  <l>That with a word ſhackled the Ocean;</l>
                  <l>He ſhall command <hi>Neptune</hi> himſelf to bring</l>
                  <l>His Trident, and preſent it to our King.</l>
                  <l>Oh do it then, great Admiral:—Away,</l>
                  <l>Let him be here againſt St. <hi>George</hi>'s day;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Charls</hi> may wear His <hi>Dieu Et Mon Droit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Thou the Noble Garter'd <hi>Honi Soit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And when thy Aged Corps ſhall yield to Fate,</l>
                  <l>God ſave that ſoul that ſav'd our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There thou ſhalt have a glorious Crown, I know,</l>
                  <l>Who Crown'dſt our King and Kingdoms here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</l>
                  <l>But who ſhall find a Pen fit for thy glory;</l>
                  <l>Or make Poſterity believe thy Story?</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Vive</hi> St. <hi>GEORGE,</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60727:11"/>
               <head>THE TRAGEDY OF Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> Late Miniſter of the Goſpel; Acted upon TOWER-HILL, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 22. 1651.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Prologue.</head>
                  <l>NEw from a ſlaughter'd Monarchs Hearſe I come,</l>
                  <l>A Mourner to a Martyr'd Prophet's Tomb:</l>
                  <l>Pardon, great <hi>Charls</hi> his Ghoſt, my Muſe had ſtood</l>
                  <l>Yet three years longer, till ſh'had wept a Flood;</l>
                  <l>Too mean a Sacrifice for Royal Blood.</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60727:11"/>
                  <l>But ſhe muſt go, Heav'n does by Thunder call</l>
                  <l>For her Attendance at <hi>LOVE's</hi> Funeral:</l>
                  <l>Forgive, great Sir, this Sacriledged in me,</l>
                  <l>The tenth Tear he muſt have, it is his Fee;</l>
                  <l>'Tis due to him, and yet 'tis ſtoln from Thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>'Twas when the Raging Dog did rule the Skies,</l>
                  <l>And with his ſcorching Face did tyrannize,</l>
                  <l>When cruel <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Whelp of that mad Star,</l>
                  <l>But ſure more fiery than his Sire by far,</l>
                  <l>Had dry'd the <hi>Northern Fife,</hi> and with his heat</l>
                  <l>Put frozen <hi>Scotland</hi> in a Bloody Sweat:</l>
                  <l>When he had conquer'd, and his furious Train</l>
                  <l>Had chas'd the North-Bear, &amp; purſu'd <hi>Charls</hi> Wain</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Orb; then 'twas thy fate</l>
                  <l>(Sweet <hi>LOVE)</hi> to be a Preſent from our State.</l>
                  <l>A greater Sacrifice there could not come,</l>
                  <l>Than a Divine, to bleed his Welcome home.</l>
                  <l>For He, and <hi>Herod</hi> think no Diſh ſo good,</l>
                  <l>As a <hi>John Baptiſts Head,</hi> ſerv'd up in Blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>ACT. I.</head>
                  <l>The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> are ſet in their High Court,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Love,</hi> like <hi>Samſon's</hi> fetch'd to make them <hi>ſport:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto the Stake the ſmiling Priſoner's brought:</l>
                  <l>Not to be try'd, but baited, moſt men thought:</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60727:12"/>
                  <l>Monſters, like Men, muſt worry him; and thus</l>
                  <l>He fights with Beaſts, like <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adams, Far, Huntington,</hi> with all the Pack</l>
                  <l>Of foiſting Hounds, were ſet upon his Back.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prideaux</hi> and <hi>Keeble</hi> ſtand and cry, Halo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o;</l>
                  <l>'T was a full Cry, and yet it would not do.</l>
                  <l>Oh how he foil'd them! Standers by did ſwear,</l>
                  <l>That he the Judge, and they the Traitors were:</l>
                  <l>For there he prov'd (although he ſeem'd a Lamb)</l>
                  <l>Stout, like a Lion, from whoſe Den he came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>ACT. II.</head>
                  <l>It is decreed; nor ſhall thy Worth, dear <hi>Love,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reſiſt their Vows, nor their Revenge remove.</l>
                  <l>Though Pray'rs were join'd to Pray'rs, &amp; tears to tears,</l>
                  <l>No Softneſs in their Rocky Hearts appears:</l>
                  <l>Nor Heav'n nor Earth abate their Fury can,</l>
                  <l>But they will have thy Head, thy Head, good Man.</l>
                  <l>Sure ſome She-Sectary longed, and in haſte</l>
                  <l>Muſt try how <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Blood did taſte.</l>
                  <l>'T is fit ſhe have the beſt, and therefore thine,</l>
                  <l>Thine muſt be broach'd, bleſt Saint! 'tis Drink di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</l>
                  <l>No ſooner was the dreadful Sentence read,</l>
                  <l>The Priſoner ſtraight bow'd his condemned Head:</l>
                  <l>And by that humble Poſture told them all,</l>
                  <l>It was a Head that did not fear a fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60727:12"/>
                  <head>ACT. III.</head>
                  <l>And now I wiſh the fatal Stroke were given;</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure our Martyr longs to be in Heaven,</l>
                  <l>AndHeav'n to have him there: one moments blow</l>
                  <l>Makes him triumphant; but here comes his wo,</l>
                  <l>His Enemies will grant a Months Suſpence,</l>
                  <l>If't be for the nonce to keep him thence:)</l>
                  <l>And that he may tread in his Saviours ways,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall be tempted too, his forty days:</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch baits too, Caſt thy ſelf but down,</l>
                  <l>Fall, and but worſhip, and your Life's your own.</l>
                  <l>Thus cry'd his Enemies; oh 'twas their pride,</l>
                  <l>To wound his Body, and his Soul beſide.</l>
                  <l>One Plot th'have more, when all their own do fail</l>
                  <l>If Devils can't, Diſciples may prevail.</l>
                  <l>Lets tempt him by his Friends, make <hi>Peter</hi> cry,</l>
                  <l>Good Maſter, Spare thy ſelf, and do not die.</l>
                  <l>One Friend entreats, a ſecond weeps, a third</l>
                  <l>Cries, Your Petition wants the other word:</l>
                  <l>I'l write it for you, ſaith a fourth; Your Life,</l>
                  <l>Your Life, Sir, cries a fifth, Pity your Wife,</l>
                  <l>And the Babe in her: Thus this Diamonds cut</l>
                  <l>By Diamonds only, and to terror put.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I hear him ſtill, You wound my heart;</l>
                  <l>Good Friends, forbear; for every word's a Dart:</l>
                  <l>'T is cruel pity, thus I do profeſs,</l>
                  <l>You'ld love me more, if you did love me leſs:</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60727:13"/>
                  <l>Friends, Children, Wife, Life, all are dear, I know</l>
                  <l>But all's too dear, if I ſhould buy them ſo.</l>
                  <l>Thus, like a rock that routs the waves, he ſtands,</l>
                  <l>And ſnaps aſunder, <hi>Sampſon</hi>-like, theſe bands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>ACT. IV.</head>
                  <l>The Day is come, the Priſoner longs to go,</l>
                  <l>And chides the ling'ring Sun for tarrying ſo:</l>
                  <l>Which bluſhing ſeems to anſwer from the Sky,</l>
                  <l>That it was loth to ſee a Martyr dye.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I heard beheaded Saints above</l>
                  <l>Call to each other, Sirs, Make room for <hi>LOVE.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who when he came to tread the fatal Stage,</l>
                  <l>(Which prov'd his Glory, and his Enemies rage)</l>
                  <l>His Blood ne'r run t'his heart, Chriſts Blood was there</l>
                  <l>Reviving, it, his own was all to ſpare:</l>
                  <l>Which riſing in his Cheeks, did ſeem to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Is this the Bloud you thirſt for? Tak't, I pray.</l>
                  <l>Spectators in his Looks ſuch Life did ſee,</l>
                  <l>That they appear'd more like to die than he.</l>
                  <l>But oh his Speech! methinks I hear it ſtill;</l>
                  <l>It raviſh'd Friends, and did his Enemies kill:</l>
                  <l>His keener Words did their ſharp Ax exceed;</l>
                  <l>That made his head, but he their hearts, to bleed:</l>
                  <l>Which he concluded with ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Prayer, and ſo</l>
                  <l>The Lamb lay down, and took the Butchers blow:</l>
                  <l>His Soul makes Heav'n ſhine brighter by a Star,</l>
                  <l>And now we're ſure there's one Saint <hi>Chriſtopher.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60727:13"/>
                  <head>ACT. V.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>LOVE</hi> lies a bleeding, and the World ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>Heav'n act a part in this black Tragedy.</l>
                  <l>The Sun no ſooner ſpy'd the Head o'th' floor,</l>
                  <l>But he pull'd in his own, and look'd no more.</l>
                  <l>The Clouds, which ſcattered, and in colours were,</l>
                  <l>Met altogether, and in black appear:</l>
                  <l>Light'nings, which fill'd the Air with blazing light,</l>
                  <l>Did ſerve for Torches at that diſmal Night:</l>
                  <l>In which, and all next day, for many hours,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n groan'd in Thunder, &amp; did weep in Showrs.</l>
                  <l>Nor do I wonder, that God thundered ſo,</l>
                  <l>When's <hi>Boanerges</hi> murdred lay below:</l>
                  <l>The High Court trembled, <hi>Prideaux, Bradſhaw, Keeble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all the guilty Rout, look'd pale and feeble.</l>
                  <l>Timerous <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and cold-hearted <hi>Drake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hold out, you need no baſe Petitions make:</l>
                  <l>Your Enemies thus Thunder-ſtruck, no doubt,</l>
                  <l>Will be beholding to you to go out.</l>
                  <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t if you will recant, now thundring Heaven</l>
                  <l>Such Approbation to <hi>Love</hi>'s cauſe hath given,</l>
                  <l>I'le add but this; Your Conſciences perhaps,</l>
                  <l>Ere long, ſhall feel far greater Thunder-claps.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60727:14"/>
                  <head>The Epilogue.</head>
                  <l>But ſtay, my Muſe grows fearful too, and muſt</l>
                  <l>Beg that theſe Lines be buried with thy Duſt:</l>
                  <l>Shelter, bleſs'd <hi>Love,</hi> this verſe within thy Shroud,</l>
                  <l>For none but Heav'n dares take thy part aloud.</l>
                  <l>The Author begs this, leſt, if it be known.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt he bewails thy Head, he loſe his own.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60727:14"/>
               <head>UPON The much to be Lamented DEATH OF THE Reverend Mr. <hi>Vines.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ARt thou gone too (thou great &amp; gallant mind)</l>
                  <l>And muſt ſuch Sneaks as I be left behind?</l>
                  <l>If thus our Horſemen and Commanders die,</l>
                  <l>What can the Infantry do then but fly?</l>
                  <l>Oh Divine <hi>Vines!</hi> tell us, why wouldſt thou go,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thou couldſt have left thy Parts below?</l>
                  <l>If there's a <hi>Metempſuchoſis</hi> indeed,</l>
                  <l>Tell us where we may find thee at our need?</l>
                  <l>Who hath thy Memory? thy Brain, thy Heart?</l>
                  <l>Whom didſt thou leave thy Tongue? (for ev'ry part</l>
                  <l>Of thee can make a Man.) What if we find</l>
                  <l>(As I'l not ſwear this Age won't change her mind)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prelacy</hi> (though her Lands are ſold) revive?</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Independency</hi> (who hopes to thrive,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60727:15"/>
                  <l>No where ſuits Trump) ſhould dare diſpute at length?</l>
                  <l>Where haſt thou left thy <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Strength,</l>
                  <l>With which thou got'ſt the Game in th' Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where the King cry'd that <hi>Vines</hi> was in the right?</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Eſſex</hi> dy'd (the Honour of our Nation)</l>
                  <l>Thou gav'ſt him a new life in thy Oration.</l>
                  <l>But when great <hi>Fairfax</hi> to his Fate ſhall yield,</l>
                  <l>Whom haſt thou left—to fetch from <hi>Naſeby</hi>-field</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th' Immortal Turf,</hi> and dreſs it with a Story,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall perpetuate his name and glory?</l>
                  <l>Where's thy rich Fancy (man?) To whom (beneath)</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou thy lofty and high ſtrain bequeath?</l>
                  <l>Tell us for thy own ſake; for none but he</l>
                  <l>That hath thy Wit, can write thy Elegie.</l>
                  <l>Till he be found, let this ſuffice, which I</l>
                  <l>Leave on thy Stone:—<hi>Here lies the Miniſtry.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60727:15"/>
               <head>TO THE MEMORY OF Mr. <hi>Jeremy Whitaker,</hi> Powerful in Prayer and Preaching, Pious in Life, Patient in Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NAy, now forbear; for pity ſake give o're,</l>
                  <l>You that would make the Clergy none, or poor:</l>
                  <l>We are made miſerable enough this year,</l>
                  <l>That we have loſt our Reverend <hi>Whitaker;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loſs above Deaus and Chapters! had but he</l>
                  <l>Liv'd ſtill and preach'd: <hi>Ziba</hi> take all (for me.)</l>
                  <l>Nay I believe had ſacrilegious hands</l>
                  <l>Finger'd our poor remains of Tithes and Lands,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt he ſurviv'd they had but pray'd in vain,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whitaker</hi> would have pray'd them back again,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60727:16"/>
                  <l>As <hi>Luther</hi> did a young mans Soul repeal,</l>
                  <l>Giv'n to the Devil under Hand and Seal,</l>
                  <l>A Chariot and an Horſeman we have loſt,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe each ſingle Pray'r incamp'd an Hoſt.</l>
                  <l>How have I heard him on ſome ſolemn Day,</l>
                  <l>When doubtful War could make all <hi>London</hi> pray)</l>
                  <l>Mount up to Heav'n with armed cries and tears,</l>
                  <l>And rout, as far as <hi>York,</hi> the Cavaliers!</l>
                  <l>Have you not ſeen an early-riſing Lark</l>
                  <l>Spring from her Turf, making the Sun her mark,</l>
                  <l>Shooting her ſelf aloft, yet higher, higher,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe had ſung her ſelf into Heaven's Quire?</l>
                  <l>Thus would he riſe in Pray'r, and in a trice</l>
                  <l>His Soul become a Bird of Paradiſe:</l>
                  <l>And if our faint Devotions Prayers be,</l>
                  <l>What can we call his leſs than Extaſie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>On his Preaching.</head>
                  <l>If with the Almighty he prevailed ſo,</l>
                  <l>Wonder not that he Wonders wrought below:</l>
                  <l>The Son of Conſolation and of Thunder</l>
                  <l>Met both in him, in others are aſunder.</l>
                  <l>He was (like <hi>Luke)</hi> Phyſician of both kinds,</l>
                  <l>Wrought Cures upon Mens Bodies &amp; their Minds,</l>
                  <l>The Falling-ſickneſs of Apoſtacy,</l>
                  <l>Dropſie of Drunkenneſs, Prides Tympany,</l>
                  <l>The Meagrim of Opinions, new or old,</l>
                  <l>Palſie of Unbelief, Charities cold,</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60727:16"/>
                  <l>Luſts burning Fever, Angers Calenture,</l>
                  <l>The Collick in the Conſcience he could cure:</l>
                  <l>Set the ſouls broken bones; by holy Art</l>
                  <l>He hath diſſolv'd the Stone in many a Heart,</l>
                  <l>Harder than that he dy'd of—O come in,</l>
                  <l>Ye multitudes whom he hath heal'd of ſin,</l>
                  <l>And thereby made his Debtors—Pay him now</l>
                  <l>Some of thoſe tears which he laid out for you;</l>
                  <l>Intereſt-tears, I mean; for ſhould you all</l>
                  <l>Weep over him both Uſe and Principal,</l>
                  <l>'Twould waſh away the Stone (which covers him)</l>
                  <l>And make his Coffin (like an Ark) to ſwim.</l>
                  <l>Now wipe thine eyes (my Muſe) &amp; ſtop thy Verſe</l>
                  <l>(Thy Ink can only ſerve to black his Hearſe,)</l>
                  <l>Yet (ſtay) i'll drop one Tear, ſigh one ſigh more,</l>
                  <l>'Tis this, although my Poetry be poor</l>
                  <l>O what a mighty Prophet ſhould I be,</l>
                  <l>Had this <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Mantle faln to me!</l>
                  <l>Oh might I live his Life! I'd be content</l>
                  <l>His ſore Diſeaſes too ſhould me torment:</l>
                  <l>And if his Patience could mine become,</l>
                  <l>I would not be afraid of Martyrdom.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60727:17"/>
               <head>UPON THE DEATH OF So many Reverend Miniſters of late.</head>
               <l>STill we do find, Black cloth wears out the firſt;</l>
               <l>And fruits that are the choiceſt keep the worſt.</l>
               <l>Such men? So many? and they die ſo faſt?</l>
               <l>They'r precious (death) on do not make ſuch waſte.</l>
               <l>Scarce have we dry'd our eyes for loſs of one,</l>
               <l>But in comes tidings that another's gone.</l>
               <l>Oh that I had my former Tears agen,</l>
               <l>(All but thoſe few laid out upon my ſin,)</l>
               <l>Had I an <hi>Helicon</hi> in either Eye,</l>
               <l>I have occaſion now to verſe them dry.</l>
               <l>Triumph (licentious Age) lift up thy Song,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Presbytery</hi> ſha'nt trouble you ere long;</l>
               <l>Thoſe that tormented you before your day,</l>
               <l>Are now apace removing out o'th' way.</l>
               <l>Yea, rather tremble <hi>(England)</hi> ſtand agaſt,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy glorious Lamps go out ſo faſt;</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60727:17"/>
               <l>When Death (like <hi>Sampſon)</hi> thus lays hold upon</l>
               <l>The Pillars of the Church,—The Building's gone.</l>
               <l>When we do ſee ſo many Stars to fall,</l>
               <l>Surely, it boads the World's great Funeral.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London,</hi> look too't, and think what Heav'n is doing</l>
               <l>Thy Flames are coming when thy <hi>Lots</hi> are going,</l>
               <l>Well may we all fear God intendeth Wars,</l>
               <l>When he commands home his Embaſſadors.</l>
               <l>That Venerable Synod, which of late</l>
               <l>Was made the Object of Mens Scorn and Hate,</l>
               <l>(For want of Copes and Mitres, not of Graces)</l>
               <l>Are now call'd up (with <hi>Moſes)</hi> and their Faces</l>
               <l>When they return, ſhall ſhine; God ſees it fit,</l>
               <l>Such an Aſſembly ſhould in Glory ſit.</l>
               <l>The learned <hi>Twiſſe</hi> went firſt, (it was his right)</l>
               <l>Then holy <hi>Palmer, Borroughs, Love, Gouge, White,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hill, Whitaker,</hi> grave <hi>Gataker,</hi> and <hi>Strong,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pern, Marſhal, Robinſon,</hi> all gone along.</l>
               <l>I have not nam'd them half: their only ſtrife</l>
               <l>Hath been (of late) who ſhould firſt part with Life.</l>
               <l>Thoſe few who yet ſurvive, ſick of this Age,</l>
               <l>Long to have done their parts, and leave the Stage.</l>
               <l>Our Engliſh <hi>Luther, Vines,</hi> (whoſe Death I weep)</l>
               <l>Stole away (and ſaid nothing) in a Sleep:</l>
               <l>Sweet (like a Swan) he preach'd that day he went,</l>
               <l>And for his Cordial took a Sacrament:</l>
               <l>Had it but been ſuſpected—he would die,</l>
               <l>His People ſure had ſtop'd him with their Cry.</l>
               <l>My blearey'd Muſe ('tis tears have made her ſo)</l>
               <l>Muſt waſh his Marble too, before ſhe go.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60727:18"/>
               <head>AN ELOGY UPON THE Earl of Eſſex HIS FUNERAL.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANd are there all the Rites that muſt be done</l>
                  <l>Thrice Noble <hi>ESSEX, Englands</hi> Champion?</l>
                  <l>Some Men, ſome Walls, ſome Horſes put in black</l>
                  <l>With the Throng ſcrambling for Sweet-meats and Sack;</l>
                  <l>A gawdy Herald, and a Velvet Hearſe,</l>
                  <l>A tattar'd Anagram with grievous Verſe,</l>
                  <l>And a ſad Sermon to conclude withall,</l>
                  <l>Shall this be ſtil'd great <hi>ESSEX</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>neral?</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60727:18"/>
                  <l>Niggardly Nation, be aſham'd of th'odds,</l>
                  <l>Leſs Valour among Heathen made men gods:</l>
                  <l>Should ſuch a General have dy'd in <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He muſt have had an Altar, not a Tomb;</l>
                  <l>And there, in ſtead of youthful Elegies,</l>
                  <l>Grave Senators had offer'd Sacrifice</l>
                  <l>To Divine <hi>Devereux:</hi> O ſor a Vote,</l>
                  <l>(Ye Lords and Commons, ye are boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o do't)</l>
                  <l>A Vote, that who is ſeen to ſmile this year,</l>
                  <l>A Vote, that who ſo brings not in a Tear,</l>
                  <l>Shall be adjudg'd Malignant: It were wiſe</l>
                  <l>T'erect an Office in the Peoples eyes,</l>
                  <l>For iſſuing forth a conſtant ſum of Tears,</l>
                  <l>There's no way elſe to pay him his Arrears:</l>
                  <l>And when w'have drein'd this Ages eyes quite dry,</l>
                  <l>Let him be wept the next in Hiſtory;</l>
                  <l>Which if Poſterity ſhall dare to doubt,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Gloſters</hi> whiſp'ring Walls ſhall ſpeak him out:</l>
                  <l>And ſo his Funeral ſhall not be done,</l>
                  <l>Till he returnith' Reſurrection.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60727:19"/>
               <head>To the Father of a very vertuous Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, Deceaſed; who deſired an obſcure Perſon to make an Elegy, &amp;c.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SIr, Be advis'd; She's not your Daughter now,</l>
                  <l>But a crown'd Saint in Heav'ns great Court, &amp; you</l>
                  <l>Muſt take heed what you offer to her Shrine;</l>
                  <l>You'l be profane, if that be not Divine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sternhold</hi> (who kill'd the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> too</l>
                  <l>In Meeter and good meaning) did not do</l>
                  <l>More, violence to Heav'n, than you to her.</l>
                  <l>If, whil'ſt you think't a kindneſs, you ſhall blur</l>
                  <l>Her Honour with my Ink: 'tis a diſgrace</l>
                  <l>To ſet black Spots upon a glorious Face.</l>
                  <l>Diſdain will burſt her Coffin (ſure) to have</l>
                  <l>Such dirty Feet as mine ſtand on her Grave.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, 'tis niggardly to weep in Verſe,</l>
                  <l>Tears without meaſure beſt become her Hearſe,</l>
                  <l>The talking Book is ſhallow, ſtill we ſee</l>
                  <l>Great Sorrows, like deep Rivers, ſilent be.</l>
                  <l>Were I <hi>Apollo's</hi> Prieſt indeed, and fit</l>
                  <l>To ſend a Poem up in flames of Wit,</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60727:19"/>
                  <l>Yet i'm but one; Sir, to her Altar's due</l>
                  <l>Whole Hecatombs of Verſe, and Poets too.</l>
                  <l>Go ſearch St. <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard, imploy choice eyes</l>
                  <l>To ſcan all Epitaphs and Elegies;</l>
                  <l>All the rich Fancies, ſacred Raptures, all</l>
                  <l>The Pearly drops which ever yet did fall</l>
                  <l>On ſpotleſs Virgins Tombs: then make your claim</l>
                  <l>Print and devote them to your Daughters name.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe vaſt <hi>Hyperboles,</hi> thoſe lofty Notes,</l>
                  <l>Which crackt the Muſes Voices, rent their throats</l>
                  <l>Offended ſcrup'lous Readers, made them think</l>
                  <l>Poetry only ſtrong Lines, and ſtrong Drink,</l>
                  <l>Allayed by her merit, ſoon will be</l>
                  <l>Reduc'd to ſober Truth, and Modeſty,</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, this counſel is but ſimple ſtuff,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Englands</hi> Divine) <hi>Reynolds</hi> hath done enough:</l>
                  <l>His Sermon is her Monument in print,</l>
                  <l>And hath more Honour than all Poems in't.</l>
                  <l>That doth not only ſpeak her Saint, and more,</l>
                  <l>Can make him one too, who but reads it o're.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reynolds</hi> records her Saint, and you may hope</l>
                  <l>That's more than canonizing by a Pope.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60727:20"/>
               <head>IN MEMORY Of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>E. T.</hi> Who dyed <hi>April</hi> 7. 1659.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IT was the Spring, and Flowers were in conteſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſmels ſhould firſt reach Heav'n, and pleaſe it beſt;</l>
                  <l>Then did <hi>Eliza</hi>'s ſweetneſs ſo ſurpaſs</l>
                  <l>All Rival Virgins, that ſhe ſent for was.</l>
                  <l>'Twas <hi>April</hi> when ſhe dy'd; no Month ſo fit</l>
                  <l>For Heav'n to be a mourner in, as it.</l>
                  <l>'Twas <hi>Eaſter</hi> too; that time did Death deviſe</l>
                  <l>Beſt for this Lamb to be a Sacrifice.</l>
                  <l>It was the Spring; The way 'twixt Heav'n &amp; Earth</l>
                  <l>Was ſweetned for her paſſage, by the Birth</l>
                  <l>Of early Flowers, which burſt their Mothers womb,</l>
                  <l>Reſoly'd to live and die upon her Tomb.</l>
                  <l>It was the Spring; Between the Earth and Sky,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe her Soul as it was paſſing by,</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60727:20"/>
                  <l>Birds fill'd the Air with Anthems, every neſt</l>
                  <l>Was on the Wing, to chaunt her to her Reſt:</l>
                  <l>Not a Pen-feathered Lark, who ne'r try'd Wing,</l>
                  <l>Nor Throat; but ventur'd then to fly, and ſing:</l>
                  <l>Following the Saint towards Heav'n, whoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance there</l>
                  <l>Dampt them, and chang'd their Notes. Then pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Air</l>
                  <l>Diſſolv'd to tears, which ſpoil'd the feather'd Train</l>
                  <l>And ſunk them to their neſts with grief again.</l>
                  <l>Mean time, me thought, I ſaw at Heav'ns fair Gate</l>
                  <l>The glorious Virgins meet, and kiſs their Mate.</l>
                  <l>They ſtood a while her Beauty to admire</l>
                  <l>Then led her to her place in their own Quire:</l>
                  <l>Which ſeem'd to be defective, untill ſhe</l>
                  <l>Added her Sweetneſs to their Harmony.</l>
                  <l>As Meddals ſcatter'd when ſome Prince goes by,</l>
                  <l>So lay the Stars that night about the Sky.</l>
                  <l>The Milky Way too, (ſince ſhe paſt it o're)</l>
                  <l>Methinks looks whiter than it was before.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60727:21"/>
               <head>AN EPITAPH Upon <hi>E. T.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>REader, didſt thou but know what ſacred Duſt</l>
                  <l>Thou tread'ſt upon, thou'dſt judg thy ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou neglect a ſhowr of tears to pay,</l>
                  <l>To waſh the Sin of thy own Feet away.</l>
                  <l>That Actor in the Play, who looking down</l>
                  <l>When he ſhould cry, <hi>O Heav'n,</hi>—was thought a Clown,</l>
                  <l>And guilty of a Soloeciſm—might have</l>
                  <l>Applauſe for ſuch an Action o're this Grave.</l>
                  <l>Here lies a piece of Heav'n, and Heav'n one day</l>
                  <l>Will ſend the beſt in Heav'n to fetch't away.</l>
                  <l>Truth is, this Lovely Virgin from her Birth</l>
                  <l>Became a conſtant ſtrife 'twixt Heav'n and Earth:</l>
                  <l>Both claim'd her, pleaded for her; either cry'd,</l>
                  <l>The Child is mine; at length they did divide:</l>
                  <l>Heav'n took her Soul; The Earth her Corps did ſeize,</l>
                  <l>Yet not in Fee, ſhe only holds by Leaſe;</l>
                  <l>With this Proviſo—when the Judge ſhall call,</l>
                  <l>Earth ſhall give up her ſhare, and Heav'n have all</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60727:21"/>
               <head>UPON The Learned Works of the Reverend DIVINE Ed. Reynolds, D. D.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>REader, who e're thou art, here thou maiſt find</l>
                  <l>Within theſe <hi>Works,</hi> a rare, rich, glorious mind</l>
                  <l>O Golden Precepts, which, alike, do ſhew</l>
                  <l>What's thy D ſtemper how to cure it too:</l>
                  <l>Do pains oppreſs thy Body? Sorrow Mind?</l>
                  <l>Draw near to God, Pray'r will acceptance find;</l>
                  <l>And then no doubt, he'll grant, thy Bodies Grief</l>
                  <l>May bring thy ſinking ſoul ſome ſmall Relief:</l>
                  <l>Do Paſſions over-top thy will? beware,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virtue conſiſts not in ſo high a Sphere:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou the Golden <hi>Medium</hi> wilt find,</l>
                  <l>Shun thou too high, and too too low a mind.</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures are gilded Nothings, which like bubbles fly,</l>
                  <l>Swoln big with Emptineſs ſo burſt and die.</l>
                  <l>Do darkeſt times of ignorance draw near?</l>
                  <l>The rather view theſe weighty Lines: nor fear,</l>
                  <l>Nor wonder much at this reſplendent Light:</l>
                  <l>Diamonds ſhine brighteſt in the darkeſt night.</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60727:22"/>
                  <l>The Merchant-man ſold all he had, to buy</l>
                  <l>The rich, rare, Goſpel Jewel: O then why</l>
                  <l>Art thou ſo backward, ſince that thou mayſt make</l>
                  <l>This Gem thine own, yea, at a cheaper rate?</l>
                  <l>The fooliſh Virgins, when their Lord of Light</l>
                  <l>Paſt by, their lights were out: So that eternal night</l>
                  <l>Was their reward, and juſt, for they that deem</l>
                  <l>Pains coſt of greater worth, ſhall ne'r be ſeen</l>
                  <l>Within his Courts, who is great, good, and juſt.</l>
                  <l>Is Folly thus repaid? Reader, we muſt</l>
                  <l>Look that it ne'r be ſaid of thee or I,</l>
                  <l>That our Negleſt ſhould cauſe our light to die.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60727:22"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <l>LOok wiſhly (friend) thou ſeldom ſeeſt ſuch men</l>
                  <l>Heav'n drops ſuch Jewels down but now and then,</l>
                  <l>One in an Age, or Nation: oh 'tis rare,</l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Reynoldſes</hi> ſhould fall to <hi>Englands</hi> ſhare!</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Rome</hi> but ſhew one ſuch, and this were He,</l>
                  <l>His Picture could not ſcape Idolatry:</l>
                  <l>Whom Papiſts (not with Superſtitious Fire)</l>
                  <l>Would dare t' adore, we juſtly may admire.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>LEarning, whoſe Forces did diſperſed lie</l>
                  <l>(Of late alarm'd by the Enemy)</l>
                  <l>Calling a Councel, did reſolve at lengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>To chuſe one General over all her ſtrength:</l>
                  <l>Divinity (who had the choice) did Name</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reynolds?</hi> All Voices center'd in the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Now here he ſtands and heads ſuch Books as bear</l>
                  <l>Truth in their Van, and Triumph in their Rear.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60727:23"/>
               <head>AN EPITAPH For a Godly Mans Tomb.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre lies a piece of Chriſt, a Star in Duſt;</l>
                  <l>A Vein of Gold, a <hi>Chind</hi> Diſh that muſt</l>
                  <l>Be us'd in Heav'n, when God ſhall Feaſt the Juſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>AN EPITAPH For a Wicked Mans Tomb.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre lies the Carkaſe of a curſed Sinner,</l>
                  <l>Doom'd to be Roaſted, for the Devil's Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60727:23"/>
               <head>A Letter to a Friend.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Generous Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ON Saturdy laſt (the Day and Weather being as ſad and dumpiſh as old <hi>Saturn</hi> himſelf) whileſt I was in my Study (my Books and my ſelf muſty and melancholy) and my proviſions for the next Day as poor as ever were made by Countrey Curate, ſometimes ſcratching that which goes for my Head, and then biting my Nails for offending my Noddle; In comes your Friendly Letter (the welcomeſt Quarter-maſter that ever came to my Houſe) to take up Quarters for that gallant Mans Works (and if ever Good Works merited, they do) Doctor <hi>Reynolds.</hi> Sir, They no ſooner entred my Study—but all my Books ſeem'd to diſappear, as the Stars do at the riſing of the Sun: You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine what fear, ſhame, confuſion, and envy, my poor Shelves diſcovered; Some poor Authors ſtood gaſping—others tumbled down, and others burſt their Bindings—reſolving to break Priſon, rather than ſtand before ſuch a Judge of Learning. Thoſe few Fathers (which I had) ſeemed to meet in a Councel, what they ſhould do, whether ſtay or depart. Old <hi>Origen</hi> began, but he was ſo full of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60727:24"/> Allegories, and whimſeys, they could not tell what to ſay to him; but ſure he and they all were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, for fear (good men) that they ſhould now be ejected in their old Age. <hi>Juſt in</hi> thought that he ſhould again be a Martyr, and burnt to light Tobacco. <hi>Tertullian</hi> began to make Apologies; and <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf fell to his Confeſſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions. As for <hi>Hierom,</hi> as good a Scholar as he was, he wiſhed himſelf again on his Pilgrimage: and my poor Country-man <hi>Bede</hi> got into a corner, and fell to his Beeds. On another ſhelf (for I have not many) my School-men looked like School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys, and ſtood with their ſtrings untied, ready un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſſed for Correction. <hi>Aquinas</hi> himſelf wiſhed he had not ſuch ſumms to reckon for; and all the Popiſh Authors I had fell to croſſing themſelves. But what a caſe (if my ſtout Folioes and old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors fainted thus) do you think my Infantry—my. Modern men, my Quarto and Octavo Striplings were in? Yea, ſome of our own Engliſh (men of many Editions, &amp; worthy to be bound and gilded) gave back, and thruſt one another: <hi>Dod</hi> and <hi>Clever</hi> were both ſilenced; Doctor <hi>Preſtons</hi> All-ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy pleaded Inſufficiency—<hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> pulled his Caps in his Eyes, and became a Child of Light in Darkneſs—As for <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> he logot for a General Redemption of them all; but his Subſizer, poor <hi>Pierce,</hi> was afraid. at the Doctors coming in, that he and his corrected Copy, ſhould be again ſent to the Houſe of Correction. As
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60727:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> for my Pamphlets and traſh, they crouded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and having no manner of Cover for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, many of them wiſh'd <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> hang'd for Printing them, and themſelves burn'd out of the way. Thus Sir, It was with my Study: But for my ſelf, oh how I was revived and raviſh'd! No ſooner did that Book, big with Chriſt, enter and ſalute me (pardon the alluſion) but my heart, like <hi>John</hi> in his Mothers belly, leap'd for joy. No ſooner did open, and taſte the Honey, but mine Eyes were enlightned, and I mended in an inſtant. The Vanity of the Creature made me ſerious, the Sinfulneſs of Sin humbled me, the Life of Chriſt quickned me; the 110 <hi>Pſalm</hi> made me ſing, the Lords Supper feaſted me,—the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> inſpired me, and the Paſſions exceedingly affected me. What ſhall I ſay, or do? I cannot hold, but muſt fall out of trotting heavy Proſe into an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Rhyming.—</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From a kind Hand there came t' enrich a place</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In my poor Study,—the rare Works and Face</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Learned Reverend</hi> Reynolds—<hi>I receive</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Book with joy—but no Gift (by your leave)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And for the Book, and for my ſelf, I vow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ne'r had Piece could make me Preach till now:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'll pay for't (Sir) And—(which I ne'r ſhall do)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When I can write ſuch—you ſhall print them too.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mean time I propheſie, this Volume will</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Make both your</hi> Roſe <hi>and</hi> Crown <hi>to flouriſh ſtill.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60727:25"/>
               <p>Sir, accept and pardon this traſh,—next Term I ſhall be in <hi>London,</hi> and then perſonally prove what I now ſet my Hand to—<hi>(viz.)</hi> That I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours moſt Cordially, R. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60727:25"/>
               <head>Alas poor Scholar, VVhither wilt thou go? OR <hi>Strange Alterations which at this time be, There's many did think they never ſhould ſee.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN a Melancholy Study,</l>
                  <l>None but my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Methought my Muſe grew muddy;</l>
                  <l>After ſeven years Reading,</l>
                  <l>And coſtly breeding,</l>
                  <l>I felt, but could find no pelf:</l>
                  <l>Into Learned Rags</l>
                  <l>I've rent my Pluſh and Satten,</l>
                  <l>And now am fit to beg</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſtead of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would I had got a Patten.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas poor Scholar! whither wilt thou go?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60727:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cambridge</hi> now I muſt leave thee,</l>
                  <l>And follow Fate,</l>
                  <l>Colledge hopes do deceive me!</l>
                  <l>I oft expected</l>
                  <l>To have been elected,</l>
                  <l>But Deſert is reprobate.</l>
                  <l>Maſters of Colledges</l>
                  <l>Have no common Graces,</l>
                  <l>And they that have Fellowſhips</l>
                  <l>Have but common Places,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that Scholars are</l>
                  <l>They muſt have handſome faces:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas poor Scholar, whither wilt thou go?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have bow'd, I have bended,</l>
                  <l>And all in hope</l>
                  <l>One day to be befriended.</l>
                  <l>I have preach'd, I have printed</l>
                  <l>What e'r I hinted,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pope:</l>
                  <l>I worſhip'd towards the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>But the Sun doth now forſake me?</l>
                  <l>I find that I am falling,</l>
                  <l>The Northern winds do ſhake me:</l>
                  <l>Would I had been upright,</l>
                  <l>For Bowing now will break me:</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60727:26"/>
                  <l>At great Preferment I aimed,</l>
                  <l>Witneſs my Silk;</l>
                  <l>But now my hopes are maimed:</l>
                  <l>I looked lately</l>
                  <l>To live moſt ſtately,</l>
                  <l>And have a Dairy of Bell-ropes Milk;</l>
                  <l>But now alas,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I muſt not flatter,</l>
                  <l>Bigamy of Steeples</l>
                  <l>Is a laughing matter;</l>
                  <l>Each man muſt have but one,</l>
                  <l>And Curates will grow fatter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas poor Scholar, whither wilt thou go?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Into ſome Country Village</l>
                  <l>Now I muſt go,</l>
                  <l>Where neither Tythe nor Tillage</l>
                  <l>The greedy Patron</l>
                  <l>And parched Matron</l>
                  <l>Swear to the Church they owe:</l>
                  <l>Yet if I can Preach,</l>
                  <l>And pray too on a ſudden,</l>
                  <l>And confure the Pope</l>
                  <l>At adventure, without ſtudying,</l>
                  <l>Then ten pounds a year,</l>
                  <l>Beſides a Sunday Pudding.</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60727:27"/>
                  <l>All the Arts I have skill in,</l>
                  <l>Divine and Humane,</l>
                  <l>Yet all's not worth a Shilling;</l>
                  <l>When the Women hear me,</l>
                  <l>They do but jeer me,</l>
                  <l>And ſay, I am profane:</l>
                  <l>Once, I remember,</l>
                  <l>I preached with a Weaver,</l>
                  <l>I quoted <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He quoted <hi>Dod</hi> and <hi>Clever;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I nothing got,</l>
                  <l>He got a Cloak and Beaver:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas poor Scholar, whither wilt thou go?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ships, Ships, Ships, I diſcover,</l>
                  <l>Croſſing the Main;</l>
                  <l>Shall I in, and go over,</l>
                  <l>Turn Jew, or Atheiſt,</l>
                  <l>Turk, or Papiſt,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>GenevA,</hi> or <hi>Amſterdam?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Biſhopricks are void</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall I thither?</l>
                  <l>Or follow <hi>Windebank</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Finch,</hi> to ſee if either</l>
                  <l>Do want a Prieſt to ſhrive them?</l>
                  <l>O no, 'tis bluſt'ring weather.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas poor Scholar, whither wilt thou go?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60727:27"/>
                  <l>Ho, ho, ho, I have hit it,</l>
                  <l>Peace good-man Fool;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a Trade will fit it;</l>
                  <l>Draw thy Indenture,</l>
                  <l>Be bound at adventure</l>
                  <l>An Apprentice to a Free-School;</l>
                  <l>There thou mayſt command</l>
                  <l>By <hi>William Lylies</hi> Charter;</l>
                  <l>There thou mayſt whip, ſtrip,</l>
                  <l>And hang, and draw, and quarter,</l>
                  <l>And commit to the Red Rod</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Tom,</hi> and <hi>Arthur.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>l, l, 'tis thither, thither will I go.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60727:28"/>
               <head>THE <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Wisbich.</hi> COCK-FIGHT.</head>
               <byline>By <hi>R. W.</hi>
               </byline>
               <lg>
                  <l>GO you tame Gallants, you that have a Name,</l>
                  <l>And would accounted be Cocks of the Game;</l>
                  <l>That have brave Spurs to ſhew for't, and can crow,</l>
                  <l>And count all Dunghil-breed, that cannot ſhow</l>
                  <l>Suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> painted plumes as yours; which think't no vice</l>
                  <l>With Cock-like luſt to tread your Cockatrice;</l>
                  <l>Though Peacocks, Weathercocks, Woodcocks you be,</l>
                  <l>If y'are not Fighting Cocks, y'are not for me.</l>
                  <l>I of two feathered Combatants will write;</l>
                  <l>And he that means to th'life to expreſs their Fight,</l>
                  <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ke his Ink the blood which they did ſpill,</l>
                  <l>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>their dying Wings muſt take his quill.</l>
                  <l>No ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> were the doubtful People ſet,</l>
                  <l>The Match made up, and all that would had bet;</l>
                  <l>But ſtraight the skilful Judges of the Play</l>
                  <l>Brought forth their ſharp-heel'd Warriors; &amp; they</l>
                  <l>Were both in Linnen Bags, as if 'twere meet</l>
                  <l>Before they dy'd, to have their Winding-ſheet.</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60727:28"/>
                  <l>Into the Pit they'r brought, and being there</l>
                  <l>Upon the Stage, the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Chanticleer</l>
                  <l>Looks ſtoutly at his ne'r-before-ſeen Foe,</l>
                  <l>And like a Challenger began to crow,</l>
                  <l>And clap his Wings, as if he would diſplay</l>
                  <l>His Warlike colours, which were black and gray.</l>
                  <l>Mean time the wary <hi>Wisbich</hi> walks and breathes</l>
                  <l>His active Body, and in fury wreaths</l>
                  <l>His comely Creſt; and often looking down,</l>
                  <l>He beats his angry Beak upon the ground.</l>
                  <l>This done, they meet, not like that coward Breed</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Aeſope</hi>'s; theſe can better fight then feed:</l>
                  <l>They ſcorn the Dunghil; 'tis their only p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ize</l>
                  <l>To dig for Pearls within each others Eyes.</l>
                  <l>They fought ſo nimbly, that 'twas hard to know,</l>
                  <l>To th' skilful, whether they did fight or no;</l>
                  <l>If that the blood which dy'd the fatal floor,</l>
                  <l>Had not born witneſs of't. Yet fought they more,</l>
                  <l>As if each wound were but a Spur to prick</l>
                  <l>Their fury forward. Lightnings not more quick</l>
                  <l>Or red, then were their Eyes: 'Twas hard to know</l>
                  <l>Whether 'twas blood, or anger made them ſo.</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure they had been out, had they not ſtood</l>
                  <l>More ſafe, being walled in each others blood.</l>
                  <l>Thus they vy'd blows; but yet, alas, at length,</l>
                  <l>Although their courage were ful tri'd, theirſtrength</l>
                  <l>And blood began to ebb. You that have ſeen</l>
                  <l>A Watry Combat on the Sea, between</l>
                  <l>Two angry-roaring-boiling Billows, how</l>
                  <l>They march, and meet, and daſh their curled brow;</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60727:29"/>
                  <l>Swelling like graves, as though they did intend</l>
                  <l>T'intomb each other, ere the quarrel end;</l>
                  <l>But when the wind is down, and bluſtring weather,</l>
                  <l>They are made <hi>friends,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweetly</hi> run together;</l>
                  <l>May think theſe Champions ſuch: their blood grows low</l>
                  <l>And they which leap'd but now, now ſcarce can go</l>
                  <l>For having left th' advantage of the Heel,</l>
                  <l>Drunk with each others blood, they only reel;</l>
                  <l>And yet they would fain fight: they came ſo near,</l>
                  <l>Methought they meant into each others ear</l>
                  <l>To whiſper wounds; and when they could not riſe</l>
                  <l>They lay and look'd blows int' each others eyes.</l>
                  <l>But now the Tragick part! After this fit,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Norfolk</hi> Cock had got the beſt of it,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Wisbich</hi> lay a dying, ſo that none,</l>
                  <l>Though ſober, but might venture ſeven to one,</l>
                  <l>Contracting, like a dying Taper, all</l>
                  <l>His ſtrength, intending with the blow to fall,</l>
                  <l>He ſtruggles up, and having taken wind,</l>
                  <l>Ventures a blow, and ſtrikes the other blind.</l>
                  <l>And now poor <hi>Norfolk,</hi> having loſt his Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Fights guided only by Antipathies:</l>
                  <l>With him, alas! the Proverb is not true,</l>
                  <l>The blows his Eyes ne'r ſaw, his heart muſt rue.</l>
                  <l>At laſt, by chance, he ſtumbling on his Foe,</l>
                  <l>Not having any ſtrength to give a blow,</l>
                  <l>He falls upon him with his wounded Head,</l>
                  <l>And makes his Conquerors wings his Feather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</l>
                  <l>His friends ran in, and being very chary,</l>
                  <l>Sent in all haſte to call a Pothecary:</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60727:29"/>
                  <l>But all in vain, his body did ſo bliſter,</l>
                  <l>That 'twas not capable of any Clyſter.</l>
                  <l>Phyſick's in vain, and 'twill not him reſtore;</l>
                  <l>Alas poor Cock, he was let blood before</l>
                  <l>Then finding himſelf weak, op'ning his Bill,</l>
                  <l>He calls a Scrivener, and thus makes his Will;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Imp.</hi> Firſt of all, let never be forgot,</l>
                  <l>My Body freely I bequeath to th' Pot,</l>
                  <l>Decently to be boyl'd; and for its Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Let it be buried in ſome hungry Womb,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> For Executors I'll have none,</l>
                  <l>But he that on my ſide laid ſeven to one;</l>
                  <l>And, like a Gentleman that he may live,</l>
                  <l>To him, and to his Heirs, my Comb I give,</l>
                  <l>Together with my Brains, that all may know,</l>
                  <l>That oftentimes his Brains did uſe to crow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> For Comfort of thoſe Weaker ones</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wives complain of, let them have my Stones</l>
                  <l>For Ladies that are light, it is my Will,</l>
                  <l>My Feathers make a Fan. And for my Bill;</l>
                  <l>I'll give a Taylor: But 'faith 'tis ſo ſhort,</l>
                  <l>I am afraid, he'll rather curſe me ſor't.</l>
                  <l>And for that worthy Doctor's ſake, who meant</l>
                  <l>To give me a Clyſter, let my Rump be ſent.</l>
                  <l>Laſtly, becauſe I find my ſelf decay,</l>
                  <l>I yield, and give to <hi>Wisbich</hi> Cock the day.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60727:30"/>
               <head>UPON THE DEATH OF <hi>Dennis Bond,</hi> Eſq; Who died four Dayes before the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw whil'ſt <hi>Whitehall</hi> wears black, and men do fear</l>
                  <l>'Tis Treaſon any Colour elſe to wear;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Mourners, like a flock of Crows, reſort</l>
                  <l>To the great Lion's Carcaſe, at the Court;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the ſad Members of the Tother Houſe</l>
                  <l>(That Mountain w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> laſt year brought forth a Mouſe)</l>
                  <l>Lament his Fall, who Madam'd all their Wives,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Thurloe</hi> wiſhes he had nine Lives;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſome lament, he dy'd without an Ax,</l>
                  <l>And fear the Funeral will coſt Tax;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt cunning <hi>Scotland</hi> counterfeits a Groan,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ireland</hi> cudgell'd into her <hi>A hone;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60727:30"/>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>England</hi> puts her Finger in her Eye,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Welchmen</hi> uſe their Leeks to make them cry;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Grief doth chime All-in, and every Tribe</l>
                  <l>Eycleped, Mayor and Aldermen, ſubſcribe</l>
                  <l>(Or make their Marks at leaſt) how ful of Sadneſs</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Oliver</hi> is dead, and eke of gladneſs</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Richard</hi> reigns! though the Slaves lie, I fear,</l>
                  <l>For their old Gowns are lin'd with Cavalier:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the ſad Poetaſters of the times</l>
                  <l>Plaiſter the Hearſe with miſerable Rhymes,</l>
                  <l>And I, poor Man, might mend my Fortune too,</l>
                  <l>As ſure as ever Lord <hi>Hewſon</hi> mended Shoo,</l>
                  <l>If I could baſte my Muſe, and make her go:</l>
                  <l>I, by that great Ghoſts leave, am well content</l>
                  <l>To wait upon a meaner Monument;</l>
                  <l>Yet fit to ſtand by this, if not above,</l>
                  <l>As having, though leſs Pomp, yet no leſs Love;</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Dennis Bond,</hi> that true bred <hi>Engliſh</hi> Squire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth, if my rude Fancy ſhould aſpire</l>
                  <l>To reach the Sinews; juſt, pious, valiant wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Able for Counſel or for Enterprize;</l>
                  <l>Fit to ſet <hi>Cato</hi> Copies, if alive,</l>
                  <l>Able to make a Bankrupt Nation thrive;</l>
                  <l>Th' Alchimy of whoſe ſingle Judgement could</l>
                  <l>Convert a Leaden Councel into Gold.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atlas</hi> of State! oh! if King <hi>Charls</hi> that's gone,</l>
                  <l>In ſtead of <hi>Digby</hi> and old <hi>Cottington,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had had one <hi>Dennis;</hi> he had ſtood till now,</l>
                  <l>And kept the Crown faſt on his Royal Brow.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60727:31"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cromwel</hi> could not out-live him; ſo our State</l>
                  <l>In one week loſt their Pilot, and his Mate:</l>
                  <l>And though he dy'd in's Bed, 'tis not deny'd;</l>
                  <l>Yet was his Head ſtruck off when <hi>Dennis</hi> dy'd.</l>
                  <l>Adieu, brave <hi>Bond!</hi> My aged Muſe ſhall burn</l>
                  <l>Her with'red Lawrel at thy ſcared Urn.</l>
                  <l>Live thine own Monument, and ſcorn a Stone;</l>
                  <l>Marbles themſelves have flaws, thy Name has none</l>
                  <l>That plat of Earth which graſps thee in her womb,</l>
                  <l>Proud of ſuch Treaſure, ſwells into a Tomb.</l>
                  <l>When the next Parliament together come,</l>
                  <l>And miſs their Weſtern Patriot from his room,</l>
                  <l>Deſpairing that their Meeting will not ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Grief will diſſolve them, no Protector need.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60727:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſome Bottles of</hi> Sack <hi>and</hi> Claret, <hi>laid in Sand, and covered with a Sheet.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ENter, and ſee this Tomb (Sirs) do not fear</l>
                  <l>No Spirits, but of Wine, will frightyou here:</l>
                  <l>Weep o're this Tomb, your Sorrows here may have</l>
                  <l>Wine for their ſweet Companions in the Grave.</l>
                  <l>A dozen <hi>Shakeſpears</hi> here interr'd do lie;</l>
                  <l>Two dozen <hi>Johnſons</hi> full of Poetry.</l>
                  <l>Did not the Mother Hogſhead, from whoſe womb</l>
                  <l>Theſe Babes ſprang forth, burſt when ſhe ſaw this Tomb,</l>
                  <l>And ſwell with grief? Did not the Butler ſink,</l>
                  <l>To ſee himſelf turn Sexton to his Drink?</l>
                  <l>'Twere commendable Sacriledge, no doubt,</l>
                  <l>Could I come at your Grave, to ſteal you out:</l>
                  <l>Howe'er, from this thy anxious Grave I will</l>
                  <l>Some virtuous Aſhes take, wherewith I'll fill</l>
                  <l>The Glaſs I preach by; for I muſt be juſt,</l>
                  <l>There lies Divinity within thy Duſt.</l>
                  <l>Unhappy Grape, could not one preſſing do,</l>
                  <l>But now alive you muſt be buryed too?</l>
                  <l>Sleep on, but ſcorn to die, immortal Liquer:</l>
                  <l>The burying of thee thus will make thee quicker:</l>
                  <l>Mean while thy Friends prayloud, that thou maiſt have</l>
                  <l>A ſpeedy Reſurrection from the Grave,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60727:32"/>
               <head>AN ESSAY Upon the late <hi>VICTORY</hi> obtained by His Royal Highneſs the Duke of York, Againſt the DUTCH, upon <hi>June</hi> 3. 1665.</head>
               <byline>By the Author of <hi>Iter Boreale.</hi>
               </byline>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOUT! I conjure thee by the powerful Names</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>CHARLES</hi> and <hi>JAMES,</hi> and their victorious Fames,</l>
                  <l>On this great Day ſet all thy Priſoners free,</l>
                  <l>(Triumphs command a Goal-Delivery)</l>
                  <l>Set them all free, leave not a limping Toe</l>
                  <l>From my <hi>Lord Chancellors</hi> to mine below;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thou giv'ſt leave this day to dance,</l>
                  <l>Thou'rt not th' old Loyal Gout, but com'ſt from <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis done, my grief obeys the Sovereign Charms,</l>
                  <l>I feel a Bonfire in my joynts, which warms</l>
                  <l>And thaws the frozen jelly; I am grown</l>
                  <l>Twenty years younger; Victory hath done</l>
                  <l>What puzled Phyſick: Give the <hi>Dutch</hi> a Rout,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Probatum eſt,</hi> 'twill cure an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gout.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60727:32"/>
                  <l>Come then, put nimble Socks upon my Feet,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall be <hi>Skippers</hi> to our <hi>Royal Fleet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which now returns in dances on our Seas,</l>
                  <l>A Conqueror above <hi>Hyperboles.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Sea which with <hi>Bucephalus</hi> doth ſcorn</l>
                  <l>Leſs then an <hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould be born</l>
                  <l>On her proud Back; but to a Loyal Rein</l>
                  <l>Yields foaming Mouth, &amp; bends her curſed Main:</l>
                  <l>And conſcious that ſhe is too ſtrait a Stage</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Charls</hi> to act on, ſwell'd with Loyal Rage,</l>
                  <l>Urgeth the <hi>Belgick</hi> and the <hi>Gallick</hi> ſhore</l>
                  <l>To yield more room, Her Maſter muſt have more,</l>
                  <l>Ingrateful Neighbours! 'twas our kinder Iſle,</l>
                  <l>With Her own Blood, made Your <hi>Geneva</hi> Stile</l>
                  <l>Writ in-ſmall Print [Poor States and ſore Perplext:]</l>
                  <l>Swel to the <hi>[HIGH AND MIGHTY LORDS]</hi> in text;</l>
                  <l>And can ye be ſuch Snakes to ſting that Breaſt</l>
                  <l>Which in your Winter gave you Warmth &amp; Reſt?</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Flemiſh Frogs,</hi> if Your Ambition thirſt</l>
                  <l>To ſwell to <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſh</hi> Greatneſs, You will burſt.</l>
                  <l>Could you believe Our Royal Head would fail</l>
                  <l>To Nod thoſe down, who fell before our Tail?</l>
                  <l>Or could Your <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by her commands,</l>
                  <l>Make <hi>London</hi> carry Coals to warm her Hands?</l>
                  <l>A bold attempt! Pray practice it no more;</l>
                  <l>We ſav'd our Coals, yet gave you fire good ſtore</l>
                  <l>It is enough; The righteous Heavens have now</l>
                  <l>Judg'd the Grand Quarrel betwixt us and you.</l>
                  <l>The Sentence is—The Surface muſt be ours,</l>
                  <l>But for the bottom of the Sea 'tis yours:</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60727:33"/>
                  <l>Thither your <hi>Opdam</hi> with ſome thouſands, are</l>
                  <l>Gone down to take poſſeſſion of your ſhare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Methinks I here great <hi>Triton</hi> ſound a Call,</l>
                  <l>And through th' affr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghted Ocean ſummon all</l>
                  <l>His ſcaly Regiments, to come and take</l>
                  <l>Part of that <hi>Feaſt</hi> which <hi>Charls</hi> their King doth make;</l>
                  <l>Where they may glut Revenge, quit the old ſcore,</l>
                  <l>And feed on thoſe who fed on them before;</l>
                  <l>Whom when they have digeſted, who can find</l>
                  <l>Whether they're fiſh, or fleſh, or what's their kind?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Van-Cod, Van-Ling, Van-Herring,</hi> will be cry'd</l>
                  <l>About their Streets; All Fiſh, ſo <hi>Dutchifi'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The States may find their <hi>Capers</hi> in their Diſh,</l>
                  <l>And meet their <hi>Admirals</hi> in butter'd Fiſh.</l>
                  <l>Thus they'l imbody and increaſe their Crew;</l>
                  <l>A cunning way to make each Dutch-man two.</l>
                  <l>And on themſelves they now muſt feed or faſt;</l>
                  <l>Their Herring Trade is brought unto its <hi>Laſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>To the KING.</head>
                  <l>GReat Sir, Belov'd of God and Man, admit</l>
                  <l>My Loyal zeal to run before my Wit.</l>
                  <l>This is my Pens miſcarriage, not a Birth;</l>
                  <l>Her haſte hath made her bring blind Puppies forth,</l>
                  <l>My aims in this attempt, are to provoke,</l>
                  <l>And kindle flames more Noble by my ſmoak;</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60727:33"/>
                  <l>My wiſp of ſtraw may ſet great Wood on Fire,</l>
                  <l>And my weak Breath Your Organs may inſpire.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt thoſe Flags y'have taken from the Dutch,</l>
                  <l>Command your <hi>Denham</hi> to hang up his Crutch,</l>
                  <l>He is a man both of his Hands and Feet,</l>
                  <l>And with great numbers can your Navy meet,</l>
                  <l>His quicker Eye Your Conqueſt can ſurvey;</l>
                  <l>His Hand, <hi>York</hi>'s Temples Crown with flouriſhing Bay</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Waller</hi> (great <hi>Poet</hi> and true <hi>Prophet</hi> too)</l>
                  <l>Whoſe curious Pencil in Rich Colours drew</l>
                  <l>The Type of this grand Triumph for your view.</l>
                  <l>(The Fiſhers (like their Herrings) bleeding new)</l>
                  <l>With the ſame hand ſhal give the World the Sights</l>
                  <l>Of what it muſt expect when <hi>England</hi> Fights.</l>
                  <l>That Son and Heir of <hi>Pindars</hi> Muſe and Fame,</l>
                  <l>Your modeſt <hi>Cowley,</hi> with Your breath will flame,</l>
                  <l>And make thoſe <hi>Belgick Beaſts,</hi> who live aſpire</l>
                  <l>To fall your Sacrifice in his pure Fire.</l>
                  <l>He ſhall proclaim Our <hi>JAMES</hi> great <hi>Neptune's Wonder,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, like a <hi>Jove,</hi> Fighting in Clouds and Thunder.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60727:34"/>
               <head>THE GRATEFUL NON-CONFORMIST: OR, Return of Thanks to Sir <hi>J. B.</hi> Knight who ſent the Author Ten CROWNS 1665.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TEn Crowns at once! and to one man! and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>As deſpicable as bad Poets be!</l>
                  <l>Who ſcarce has Wit (if you require the ſame)</l>
                  <l>To make an Anagram upon your Name!</l>
                  <l>Or to out-rime a Barber, or prepare</l>
                  <l>An Epitaph to ſerve a <hi>Quinbrough</hi> Mayer!</l>
                  <l>A limping <hi>Levite!</hi> who ſcarce in his prime</l>
                  <l>Could woe an <hi>Abigal,</hi> or ſay Grace in rhime!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ten Crowns to ſuch a Thing! Friend, 'tis a do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Able to raiſe dead <hi>Ben,</hi> or <hi>Davenant</hi>'s Noſe;</l>
                  <l>Able to make a Courtier prove a Friend,</l>
                  <l>And more then all of them in Victuals ſpend.</l>
                  <l>This free, free-Parliament, whoſe gift doth ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Full five and twenty hundred thouſand pound:</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60727:34"/>
                  <l>You have out-done them, for yours was your own,</l>
                  <l>And ſome of it ſhall laſt when theirs is gon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ten Crowns at once! and now at ſuch a time,</l>
                  <l>When Love to ſuch as I am, is a Crime</l>
                  <l>Greater then his Recorded in <hi>Jane Shore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who gave but one poor loaf to the ſtarv'd Whore.</l>
                  <l>What, now to help a Non-Conformiſt! Now</l>
                  <l>When Miniſters are broke that will not bow!</l>
                  <l>When 'tis to be unbleſt to be ungirt!</l>
                  <l>To wear no Surplice, doth deſerve no ſhirt:</l>
                  <l>No Broth, no Meat; no Service, no Protection;</l>
                  <l>No Croſs, no Coin; no Collect, no Collection!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You are a daring Knight, thus to be kind;</l>
                  <l>If truſty <hi>Roger</hi> get it in the wind</l>
                  <l>Hee'l ſmell a Plot, a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot,</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially for what you gave the <hi>Scot!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if the Spiritual Court take fire from Crack,</l>
                  <l>They'l clap a Pariter upon your back:</l>
                  <l>Shall make you ſhrug, as if you wore the Collar</l>
                  <l>Of a Caſhier'd Red-coat, or poor Scholar.</l>
                  <l>What will you plead, Sir, if they put you to't?</l>
                  <l>Was it the Doctor, or the Knight did do't?</l>
                  <l>Did you as Doctor, flux ſome Uſurer?</l>
                  <l>And with your quick, did his dull Silver ſtir?</l>
                  <l>Or did your Zeal, you a Knight-Templer make,</l>
                  <l>To give the Church the booties you ſhould take?</l>
                  <l>Or was it your deſire to beg Applauſe?</l>
                  <l>Or ſhew affection to the good old Cauſe?</l>
                  <l>Was't to feed Faction, or uphold the ſtickle</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the old Church and new Conventicle?</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60727:35"/>
                  <l>No, none of theſe, but I have hit the thing,</l>
                  <l>It was becauſe you knew I lov'd the King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ten Crowns at once! Sir you'l ſuſpected be</l>
                  <l>For no good Proteſtant, you are ſo free.</l>
                  <l>So much at once! ſure you ne'r gave before,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe, I doubt, mean to do ſo no more.</l>
                  <l>This is enough to make a man proteſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religio Medici</hi> to be the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Chriſtians, for whoſe ſakes we are undone,</l>
                  <l>Would have cry'd out, oh! 'tis too much for one</l>
                  <l>Either to give or take! what needs this waſt?</l>
                  <l>Oh, how they love to have us keep a Faſt!</l>
                  <l>Five private Meetings, (where at each, four men</l>
                  <l>In black coats, and white caps, (you'l call them then</l>
                  <l>A teem of Miniſters) have tug'd all day,</l>
                  <l>Deſerving Provender, but ſcarce got hey;</l>
                  <l>Where I my ſelf have drawn my part ſome hours,</l>
                  <l>Have not afforded ſuch return as yours.</l>
                  <l>I'de wiſh them watch, and keep me ſober ſtill;</l>
                  <l>Not want of guilt in them, nor want of will</l>
                  <l>In me, but want of Wine does make me lame,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe I'de ſacrifice them to the flame</l>
                  <l>Of a high blazing Satyr. Here's a man</l>
                  <l>Who ne'r pretended at your rates, yet can</l>
                  <l>More freely feed us, with Wine and good Diſhes,</l>
                  <l>Then they (yet that's their alms) with ſighs and wiſhes</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh, for a Rapture! how ſhall I deſcribe</l>
                  <l>The love of thouſands to their Reading Tribe!</l>
                  <l>Who ſo maintaind them, when they loſt their places</l>
                  <l>They did not looſe one pimple from their faces;</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60727:35"/>
                  <l>But after all, full fraught with fleſh and flaggon,</l>
                  <l>Came forth like Monks, or Prieſts of Bel &amp; Dragon</l>
                  <l>One would have judg'd by their high looks &amp; ſmels</l>
                  <l>They had been kept in Cellars, not in Cells:</l>
                  <l>Where they grew big and batten'd; without doubt</l>
                  <l>Some that went Firkins in, came Hogs heads out.</l>
                  <l>But ours in two years time are skin and bones,</l>
                  <l>And look like <hi>Gran-dames,</hi> or old <hi>Apple Johns:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One <hi>Lazarus</hi> amongſt us was too much,</l>
                  <l>But ere't be long we all ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> look like ſuch;</l>
                  <l>And when that comes to paſs, the world ſhall ſee,</l>
                  <l>Who are the Ghoſtly Fathers, they or we;</l>
                  <l>And then our bellies (without better fare)</l>
                  <l>Will be as empty as their Noddles are:</l>
                  <l>Though we are ſilent, our guts will not be ſo,</l>
                  <l>But make a Conventicle as they go:</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Colon</hi> peace, and ceaſe thy croking din,</l>
                  <l>Thou art condemn'd to be a <hi>Chitterlin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ggardly Puritans! bluſh at the odds</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the <hi>Bonners</hi> and the meagre <hi>Dodds;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You give your Drink in Thimbles, they in Bowls,</l>
                  <l>Your Church is poor St. <hi>Faiths</hi> and theirs is <hi>Pauls;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And whilſt you Prieſts and Altars do deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>Your ſelves prove Prieſts, and we your Sacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But why do I permit my Muſe to whine?</l>
                  <l>I wiſh my Brethren all ſuch cheeks as mine,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that wiſh us well, ſuch hearts as thine,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Noble <hi>Baber,</hi> I have choſen you</l>
                  <l>For my Phyſitian, and my Champion too;</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60727:36"/>
                  <l>Give me but ſometimes ſuch a doſe, and I</l>
                  <l>Will ne'r wiſh other Cordial till I die,</l>
                  <l>And then Proclaim you a moſt Valiant Knight,</l>
                  <l>(Shew but ſuch Mettle) though you never Fight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60727:36"/>
               <head>A POEM UPON THE Impriſonment OF M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> CALAMY In <hi>NEWGATE.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis Page I ſend you Sir, your <hi>Newgate</hi> Fate</l>
                  <l>Not to condole, but to congratulate.</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60727:37"/>
                  <l>I envy not our Mitred men, their Places,</l>
                  <l>Their rich Preferments, nor their richer <hi>Faces:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſee them Steeple upon Steeple ſet,</l>
                  <l>As if they meant that way to Heaven to get.</l>
                  <l>I can behold them take into their Gills</l>
                  <l>A doſe of Churches, as men ſwallow Pills,</l>
                  <l>And never grieve at it: Let them ſwim in Wine</l>
                  <l>While others drown in tears, i'le not repine,</l>
                  <l>But my heart truly grudges (I confeſs)</l>
                  <l>That you thus loaded are with happineſs;</l>
                  <l>For ſo it is: And you more bleſſed are</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Peters</hi> Chain, than if you ſet in's Chair.</l>
                  <l>One Sermon hath preferr'd you ſo much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</l>
                  <l>A man could ſcarce have had from Biſhop <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt we (your Brethren) poor Erraticks be,</l>
                  <l>You are a glorious fixed Star we ſee.</l>
                  <l>Hundreds of us turn out of Houſe and Home,</l>
                  <l>To a ſafe Habitation you are come.</l>
                  <l>What though it be a Goal? Shame and Diſgrace</l>
                  <l>Riſe only from the Crime, not from the place.</l>
                  <l>Who thinks reproach or injuries is done</l>
                  <l>By an Eclipſe to the unſpotted <hi>Sun?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He only by that black upon his brow</l>
                  <l>Allures ſpectators more; and ſo do you.</l>
                  <l>Let me find Honey, though upon a Rod,</l>
                  <l>And prize the Priſon, where my Keeper's <hi>God:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60727:37"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Newgate</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> were <hi>Heav'n,</hi> if Chriſt were there,</l>
                  <l>He made the Stable ſo, and Sepulcher.</l>
                  <l>Indeed the place did for your preſence call;</l>
                  <l>Priſons do want perfuming moſt of all.</l>
                  <l>Thanks to the Biſhop, and his good Lord Mayor,</l>
                  <l>Who turn'd the Den of Thieves into a Houſe of Prayer:</l>
                  <l>And may ſome Thief by you converted be,</l>
                  <l>Like him who ſuffer'd in Chriſts company.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now would I had ſight of your <hi>Mittimus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fain would I know why you are dealt with thus.</l>
                  <l>Jaylor, ſet forth your Priſoner at the Bar,</l>
                  <l>Sir, you ſhall hear what your offences are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Firſt, It is prov'd that you being dead in Law</l>
                  <l>(As if you car'd not for that death a ſtraw)</l>
                  <l>Did walk and haunt your Church, as if you'ld ſcar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</l>
                  <l>Away the Reader and his Common-Prayer.</l>
                  <l>Nay 'twill be prov'd you did not only walk,</l>
                  <l>But like a <hi>Puritan</hi> your <hi>Ghoſt</hi> did talk.</l>
                  <l>Dead, and yet Preach! theſe <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſlaves</l>
                  <l>Will not give over Preaching in their Graves.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> You play'd the Thief, and ift be ſo,</l>
                  <l>Good reaſon (Sir) to <hi>Newgate</hi> you ſhould go:</l>
                  <l>And now you're there, ſome dare to ſwear you are</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Pick-pocket that e're came there:</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60727:38"/>
                  <l>Your Wife too, little better then your ſelf you make</l>
                  <l>She is th' Receiver of each Purſe you take.</l>
                  <l>But your great Theft, you act it in your Church,</l>
                  <l>(I do not mean you did your Sermon lurch,</l>
                  <l>That's crime <hi>Canonical)</hi> but you did pray</l>
                  <l>And preach, ſo that you ſtole mens hearts away.</l>
                  <l>So that good man to whom your place doth fall,</l>
                  <l>Will find they have no heart for him at all:</l>
                  <l>This Felony deſerv'd Impriſonment;</l>
                  <l>What can't you <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> be content</l>
                  <l>Sermons to make except you preach them too;</l>
                  <l>They that your places have, this Work can do.</l>
                  <l>Thirdly, 'tis prov'd, when you pray moſt devout</l>
                  <l>For all good men, you leave the Biſhops out:</l>
                  <l>This makes Seer <hi>Sheldon</hi> by his powerful ſpel</l>
                  <l>Conjure and lay you ſafe in <hi>Newgate</hi>-hell:</l>
                  <l>Would I were there too, I ſhould like it wel.</l>
                  <l>I would you durſt ſwap puniſhment with me;</l>
                  <l>Pain makes me fitter for the company</l>
                  <l>Of roaring boys; and you may lie a bed,</l>
                  <l>Now your Name's up; pray do it in my ſtead,</l>
                  <l>And if it be deny'd us to change places,</l>
                  <l>Let us for ſympathy compare our caſes;</l>
                  <l>For if in ſuffering we both agree,</l>
                  <l>Sir, I may challenge you to pity me:</l>
                  <l>I am the older Goal-bird; my hard fate</l>
                  <l>Hath kept me twenty years in <hi>Cripple-gate;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Biſhop Gout,</hi> that Lordly proud diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Took my fat body for his Dioceſs,</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60727:38"/>
                  <l>Where he keeps Court, there viſits every Limb,</l>
                  <l>And makes them <hi>(Levite</hi>-like) conform to him,</l>
                  <l>Severely he doth Article each joint,</l>
                  <l>And makes enquiry into every point:</l>
                  <l>A bitter enemy to preaching; he</l>
                  <l>Hath half a year ſometimes ſuſpended me:</l>
                  <l>And if he find me painful in my ſtation,</l>
                  <l>Down I am ſure to go next Viſitation:</l>
                  <l>He binds up, looſeth; ſets up and pulls down;</l>
                  <l>Pretends he draws ill humours from the Crown:</l>
                  <l>But I am ſure he maketh ſuch ado,</l>
                  <l>His humors trouble Head and members too:</l>
                  <l>He hath me now in hand, and e're he goes,</l>
                  <l>I fear for <hi>Hereticks</hi> he'l burn my toes.</l>
                  <l>O! I would give all I am worth, a fee,</l>
                  <l>That from his juriſdiction I were free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now Sir, you find our ſufferitgs do agree,</l>
                  <l>One Biſhop clapt up you, another me:</l>
                  <l>But oh! the difference too is very great,</l>
                  <l>You are allow'd to walk, to drink and eat,</l>
                  <l>I want them all, and never a penny get.</l>
                  <l>And though you be debarr'd your liberty,</l>
                  <l>Yet all your Viſitors I hope are free,</l>
                  <l>Good Men, good Women, and good Angels come</l>
                  <l>And make your Priſon better then your home.</l>
                  <l>Now may it be ſo till your foes repent</l>
                  <l>They gave you ſuch a rich Impriſonment.</l>
                  <l>May for the greater comfort of your lives,</l>
                  <l>Your lying in be better then your Wives.</l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:60727:39"/>
                  <l>May you a thouſand friendly papers ſee,</l>
                  <l>And none prove empty, except this from me.</l>
                  <l>And if you ſtay may I come keep your door,</l>
                  <l>Then farewel Parſonage, I ſhall ne'r be poor.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60727:39"/>
               <head>ON THE DEATH OF M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> CALAMY, <hi>Not known to the Author of a long time after.</hi> Anno 1667.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANd muſt our Deaths be ſilenc'd too! I gueſs</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſome dumb Devil hath poſſeſt the Preſs;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calamy</hi> dead without a Publication!</l>
                  <l>'Tis great injuſtice to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation:</l>
                  <l>For had this Prophet's Funeral been known,</l>
                  <l>It muſt have had an Univerſal Groan;</l>
                  <l>Afflicted <hi>London</hi> would then have been found</l>
                  <l>In the ſame year to be both burn'd and drown'd;</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60727:40"/>
                  <l>And thoſe who found no Tears their flames to quench,</l>
                  <l>Would yet have wept a Showre, his Herſe to drench.</l>
                  <l>Methinks the Man who ſtuffs the Weekly Sheet,</l>
                  <l>With fine New-Nothings, what hard Names did meet.</l>
                  <l>The Emp'reſs, how her Petticoat was lac'd,</l>
                  <l>And how her Lacquyes Liveries were ſac'd;</l>
                  <l>What's her chief Woman's Name; what Dons do bring</l>
                  <l>Almonds and Figs to <hi>Spain</hi>'s great little King:</l>
                  <l>Is much concern'd if the Pope's Toe but akes,</l>
                  <l>When he breaks Wind, and when a Purge he takes;</l>
                  <l>He who can gravely advertiſe, and tell</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Lockier</hi> and <hi>Ronland Pippin</hi> dwell;</l>
                  <l>Where a Black Box or Green-Bag was loſt;</l>
                  <l>And who was Knighted, though not what it coſt:</l>
                  <l>Methinks he might have thought it worth the while,</l>
                  <l>Though not to tell us who the State begnile,</l>
                  <l>Or what new Conqueſt <hi>England</hi> hath acquired;</l>
                  <l>Nor that poor Trifle who the City fired;</l>
                  <l>Though not how Popery exalts its head,</l>
                  <l>And Prieſts and Jeſuits their poyſon ſpread;</l>
                  <l>Yet in ſwoln Characters he might let fly,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Presbyterians have loſt an Eye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60727:40"/>
                  <l>Had <hi>Crackf—</hi>'s Fiddle been in tune, (but he</l>
                  <l>Is now a Silenc'd Man as well as We)</l>
                  <l>He had ſtruck up loud Muſick, and had plaid</l>
                  <l>A Jig for joy that <hi>Calamy</hi> was laid;</l>
                  <l>He would have told how many Coaches went;</l>
                  <l>How many Lords and Ladies did lament;</l>
                  <l>What Handkerchiefs were ſent, and in them Gold</l>
                  <l>To wipe the Widows, he would have told;</l>
                  <l>All had come out, and we beholden all</l>
                  <l>To him, for th' ovreflowing of his gall.</l>
                  <l>But why do I thus Rant without a cauſe?</l>
                  <l>Is not Concealment Policy? Whoſe Laws</l>
                  <l>My ſilly peeviſh Muſe doth ill t'oppoſe:</l>
                  <l>For publick Loſſes no Man ſhould diſcloſe;</l>
                  <l>And ſuch was this, a greater loſs by far,</l>
                  <l>One Man of God then twenty Men of War;</l>
                  <l>It was a King, who when a Prophet dy'd,</l>
                  <l>Wept over him, and Father, Father cry'd.</l>
                  <l>O if thy Life and Miniſtry be done,</l>
                  <l>My Chariots and Horſemen, ſtrength is gone.</l>
                  <l>I muſt ſpeak ſober words, for well I know</l>
                  <l>If Saints in Heaven do hear us here below,</l>
                  <l>A lye, though in his Praiſe, would make him frown,</l>
                  <l>And chide me, when with <hi>Jeſus</hi> he comes down</l>
                  <l>To judge the World.—This little He,</l>
                  <l>This ſilly, ſickly, ſilenc'd <hi>Calamy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aldermanbury's</hi> Curate, and no more,</l>
                  <l>Though he a mighty Miter might have wore,</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60727:41"/>
                  <l>Could have vi'd Intereſt in God or Man,</l>
                  <l>With the moſt pompous Metropolitan:</l>
                  <l>How have we known him captivate a throng,</l>
                  <l>And made a Sermon twenty thouſand ſtrong;</l>
                  <l>And though black-mouths his Loyalty did charge,</l>
                  <l>How ſtrong his tug was at the Royal Barge,</l>
                  <l>To hale it home, great <hi>GEORGE</hi> can well at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,</l>
                  <l>Then, when poor Prelacy lay dead in'ts neſt;</l>
                  <l>For if a Collect could not fetch him home,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> muſt ſtay out, that Intereſt was mum.</l>
                  <l>Nor did Ambition of a Miter, make</l>
                  <l>Him ſerve the Crown, it was for Conſcience<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake.</l>
                  <l>Unbribed Loyalty! his higheſt reach</l>
                  <l>Was to be Maſter <hi>Calamy,</hi> and preach.</l>
                  <l>He bleſs'd the King, who Biſhop him did name,</l>
                  <l>And I bleſs him who did refuſe the ſame.</l>
                  <l>O! had our Reverend Clergy been as free</l>
                  <l>To ſerve their Prince without Reward, as he,</l>
                  <l>They might have had leſs Wealth with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Love:</l>
                  <l>Envy, like Winds, endangers things above;</l>
                  <l>Worth, not Advancement, doth beget eſteem;</l>
                  <l>The higheſt Weathercock the leaſt doth ſeem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If you would know of what diſeaſe he dy'd,</l>
                  <l>His grief was Chronical it is reply'd.</l>
                  <l>For had he opened been by Surgeons art,</l>
                  <l>They had found <hi>London</hi> burning in his heart;</l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60727:41"/>
                  <l>How many Meſſengers of death did he</l>
                  <l>Receive with Chriſtian Magnanimity!</l>
                  <l>The Stone, Gout, Dropſie, Ills which did ariſe</l>
                  <l>Form Griefs and Studies, not from Luxuries;</l>
                  <l>The Megrim too, which ſtill ſtrikes at the Head;</l>
                  <l>Theſe he ſtood under, and ſcarce ſtaggered.</l>
                  <l>Might he but work, though loaded with theſe Chains,</l>
                  <l>He Pray'd and Preach'd, and ſung away his pains.</l>
                  <l>Then by a fatal Bill he was ſtruck dead,</l>
                  <l>And though that blow he ne're recovered,</l>
                  <l>(For he remained ſpeechleſs to his cloſe)</l>
                  <l>Yet did he breath, and breath out Prayers for thoſe.</l>
                  <l>From whom he had that wound: he liv'd to hear</l>
                  <l>An hundred thouſand buried in one Year,</l>
                  <l>In his Dear City; over which he wept,</l>
                  <l>And many Faſts to keep off Judgments kept;</l>
                  <l>Yet, yet he liv'd, ſtout heart, he liv'd to be</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd, driv'n out, and kept out, liv'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>Wars, Blazing-Stars, Torches, which Heav'n nev'r burns,</l>
                  <l>But to light Kings or Kingdoms to their Urns.</l>
                  <l>He liv'd to ſee the Glory of our Iſle,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>London,</hi> conſumed in its Funeral Pile.</l>
                  <l>He liv'd to ſee that leſſer day of Doom,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>London,</hi> the Prieſts Burnt-ſacrifice to <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:60727:42"/>
                  <l>That blow he could not ſtand, but with that Fire,</l>
                  <l>As with a Burning Feaver, did expire.</l>
                  <l>Thus dy'd this Saint, of whom it muſt be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>He dy'd a Martyr, though he dy'd in's bed.</l>
                  <l>So Father <hi>Eli</hi> in the Sacred page</l>
                  <l>Sat quivering with fear, as much as age,</l>
                  <l>Longing to know, yet loth to ask the News,</l>
                  <l>How it far'd with the Army of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſrael flies,</hi> that ſtruck his Palſie-head;</l>
                  <l>The next blow ſtunned him, <hi>Your Sons are dead;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But when the third ſtroke came, <hi>The Ark is lost;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His heart was wounded, and his life it coſt.</l>
                  <l>Thus fell this Father, and we well do know</l>
                  <l>He fear'd our Ark was going long ago.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60727:42"/>
               <head>The EPITAPH.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HEre a poor Miniſter of Chriſt doth lie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who did</hi> INDEED <hi>a Biſhoprick deny.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When his Lord comes, then, then the World ſhall ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such bumble Ones, the riſing-Men ſhall be.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How many Saints whom he had ſent before,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shouted to ſee him enter Heavens door:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There his bleſt Soul beholds the face of God,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>While we below groan out our</hi> Ichabod.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Under his burned-Church his Body lies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſhall it ſelf a glorious Temple riſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May his kind flock when a new Church they make,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Call it</hi> St. Edmundsbury <hi>for his ſake.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:60727:43"/>
               <head>THE Loyal-Nonconformiſt; OR An Account what he dare ſwear and what he dare not ſwear. Publiſhed in the year, 1666.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Fear an Oath, before I ſwear to take it;</l>
                  <l>And well I may, for 'tis the Oath of God:</l>
                  <l>I fear an Oath, when I have ſworn, to break it:</l>
                  <l>And well I may, for Vengeance hath a Rod.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet I may ſwear, and muſt too, 'tis due</l>
                  <l>Both to my Heav'nly, and my Earthly King;</l>
                  <l>If I aſſent, it muſt be full and true;</l>
                  <l>And if I promiſe, I muſt do the thing,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60727:43"/>
                  <l>I am no <hi>Quaker,</hi> not at all to ſwear;</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Papiſt,</hi> to ſwear Eaſt, and mean the Weſt;</l>
                  <l>But am a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and ſhall declare</l>
                  <l>What <hi>I cannot,</hi> and what <hi>I can</hi> proteſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I never will endeavour Alteration</l>
                  <l>Of Monarchy, nor of that Royal Name,</l>
                  <l>Which God hath choſen to command this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                  <l>But will maintain his Perſon, Crown and</l>
                  <l>Fame:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What he commands, if <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſay not nay,</l>
                  <l>(For <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a greater King then he)</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Conſcience-ſake,</hi> not <hi>Fear,</hi> I will obey;</l>
                  <l>And if not <hi>Active, Paſſive</hi> I will be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'll pray that all his Subjects may agree,</l>
                  <l>And never more be crumbled into parts;</l>
                  <l>I will endeavour that his Majeſtie</l>
                  <l>May not be King of <hi>Clubs,</hi> but King of <hi>Hearts.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Royal Oak</hi> I ſwear I will defend;</l>
                  <l>But for the <hi>lvy</hi> which doth hug it ſo,</l>
                  <l>I ſwear that is a Thief, and not a friend,</l>
                  <l>And about Steeples fitter far to grow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Civil-Government I will obey;</l>
                  <l>But for Church-Policy I ſwear I doubt it;</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60727:44"/>
                  <l>And if my Bible want th' <hi>Apocrypha,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'l ſwear my Book may be compleat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I dare not ſwear Church-Government is right</l>
                  <l>As it ſhould be; but this I dare to ſwear,</l>
                  <l>(If they ſhould put me to't) the Biſhops might</l>
                  <l>Do better, and be better than they are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor will I ſwear for all that they are worth,</l>
                  <l>That Biſhopricks will ſtand, and Doomſday ſee;</l>
                  <l>And yet I'l ſwear the Goſpel holdeth forth</l>
                  <l>Chriſt with his Miniſters till then will be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That <hi>Peter</hi> was a Prelat they aver;</l>
                  <l>But I'l not ſwear't when all is ſaid and done:</l>
                  <l>But I dare ſwear, and hope I ſhall not err,</l>
                  <l>He preach'd a hundred Sermons to their one.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peter</hi> a Fiſher was, and he caught Men:</l>
                  <l>And they have Nets, and in them catch Men too;</l>
                  <l>Yet I'l not ſwear they are alike, for them</l>
                  <l>He caught he ſav'd: theſe catch, and them undo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I dare not ſwear that Courts Eccleſiaſtick</l>
                  <l>Do in their Laws make juſt and gentle Votes;</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60727:44"/>
                  <l>But I'l be ſworn that <hi>Burton, Pryn</hi> and <hi>Baſtwick</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were once <hi>Ear-witneſſes</hi> of harſher Notes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Archdeacons, Deans and Chapters are brave men,</l>
                  <l>By Canon, not by Scripture: but to this,</l>
                  <l>If I be call'd, I'l ſwear, and ſwear agen,</l>
                  <l>That no ſuch <hi>Chapter</hi> in my Bible is.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'll not condemn thoſe <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who</l>
                  <l>Refuſed Biſhopricks, and might have had'em:</l>
                  <l>But Miſtris <hi>Calamy</hi> I'll ſwear doth do</l>
                  <l>As well as if ſhe were a <hi>Spiritual Madam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will not ſwear, that they who this Oath take,</l>
                  <l>Will for Religion e're lay down their Lives:</l>
                  <l>But I will ſwear they will good Juglers make,</l>
                  <l>Who can already ſwallow down ſuch Knives.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Holy Veſtments I'll not take an Oath</l>
                  <l>Which Linen moſt Canonical may be;</l>
                  <l>Some are for <hi>Lawn,</hi> ſome <hi>Holland,</hi> ſome <hi>Scotſ-cloth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Hemp</hi> for ſome is fitter than all three.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> had a Cloak, and Books, and Parchments too;</l>
                  <l>But that he wore a <hi>Surplice</hi> I'll not ſwear,</l>
                  <l>Nor that his Parchments did his <hi>Orders</hi> ſhew,</l>
                  <l>Or in his Books there was a <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60727:45"/>
                  <l>I owe aſſiſtance to the King by Oath;</l>
                  <l>And if he pleaſe to put the Biſhops down,</l>
                  <l>As who knows what may be, I ſhould be loth</l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Tom Beckets</hi> Miter puſh Crown</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet Church-Government I do allow,</l>
                  <l>And am contented Biſhops be the men;</l>
                  <l>And that I ſpeak in earneſt, here I vow</l>
                  <l>Where we have one, I wiſh we might have ten.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In fine, the Civil Power I'll obey,</l>
                  <l>And ſeek the Peace and Welfare of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</l>
                  <l>If this won't do, I know not what to ſay,</l>
                  <l>But farewel <hi>London,</hi> farewel <hi>Corporation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:45"/>
            <div type="title_page">
               <p>THE RECANTATION Of A Penitent PROTEUS; OR, <hi>The</hi> CHANGLING.</p>
               <p>As it was acted with good Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe in <hi>St. Maries</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and <hi>St. Pauls</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> 1663.</p>
               <p>To the Tune of Dr. Fauſtus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>London,</hi> Re-printed in the year, 1668.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb facs="tcp:60727:46"/>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60727:46"/>
               <head>Proteus <hi>his penal Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpeaking alone in the Tyring-houſe before his entring the Pulpit.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OH I am almoſt mad, 'twould make one ſo,</l>
                  <l>To ſee which way <hi>Prefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ents</hi> game doth go.</l>
                  <l>I ever thought I had her in the <hi>Wind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And yet I'm caſt above <hi>three years</hi> behind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Three times</hi> already I have <hi>turn'd</hi> my Coat;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Three times</hi> already I have <hi>chang'd</hi> my Note:</l>
                  <l>Il'e make it <hi>four</hi> and <hi>four and twenty</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>And turn the Compaſs round ere I'le give ore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Love to <hi>Church-members</hi> I will give no more;</l>
                  <l>For how I'le only court the <hi>Scarlet Whore.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'le ask the <hi>Biſhops</hi> bleſſing; and good-night</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Thomas Goodwyn,</hi> and his <hi>Child of Light.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60727:47"/>
                  <l>Poor man, he wears his Capps too much in's eyes</l>
                  <l>To be my Guide, No, I muſt be <hi>more wiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On all my <hi>Brethren</hi> I will look awry,</l>
                  <l>And cry, <hi>Stand farther off</hi> to <hi>Philip Nye.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ambition,</hi> my great Goddeſs and my Muſe,</l>
                  <l>Inſpire thy <hi>Prophets</hi> all ſuch Arts to uſe,</l>
                  <l>As may exalt; Betwixt this and my Grave</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Miter,</hi> or a <hi>Halter,</hi> I muſt have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me <hi>(Ambition)</hi> prethee tell me why</l>
                  <l>So many <hi>Dunces</hi> Doctors and not I?</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Scarlet Gown</hi> I muſt and will obtain,</l>
                  <l>I cannot elſe commence a <hi>Prieſt in grain.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Among the <hi>Doctors</hi> I can get no room</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>I recant;</hi> that is my ſhameful doom.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hang ſhame,</hi> I'le do it, and my end's to gain,</l>
                  <l>I'le <hi>cant, recant,</hi> and <hi>re-recant</hi> again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now help me great <hi>Ambition,</hi> for thy ſake</l>
                  <l>To <hi>break my ſleep,</hi> to <hi>break my Brains,</hi> to <hi>break</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> and ſo to act my part,</l>
                  <l>That men may think I have a <hi>broken Heart.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When I do preach my <hi>tears do trickle down;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But in my <hi>ſleeve</hi> (my Caſſock ſleeves and Gown)</l>
                  <l>I <hi>laugh,</hi> to think how by my <hi>whining trade</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So many Fools in one day I have made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60727:47"/>
                  <l>Help me my <hi>Muſe,</hi> a <hi>new Song</hi> I deſire</l>
                  <l>By thee may be prepared for the <hi>Quire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That when my <hi>Recantation Sermon's</hi> done,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Penitential Anthem</hi> may be ſung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But yet one thing ere I begin, I crave</l>
                  <l>A benefit, which Poets uſe to have,</l>
                  <l>That now and then, to make my Rimes agree,</l>
                  <l>What ends in <hi>Lie,</hi> may be pronounced <hi>LEE.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Second Part; Or,</hi> the Changling in the Pulpit. <hi>To the ſame Tune.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>ATtend good People, lay by ſcoffs and ſcorns,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Round-beads</hi> all this day pull in their <hi>Horns,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But let <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and brave <hi>Caveliers</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto my doleful Tone prick up their Ears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60727:48"/>
                  <l>Take from my neck this <hi>Robe,</hi> a <hi>Rop's</hi> more fit;</l>
                  <l>And turn this <hi>Surplice</hi> to a <hi>Penance-ſheet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This Pulpit is too good to act my part,</l>
                  <l>More fit to preach at <hi>Tyburn</hi> in a Cart:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There I deſerv'd t' have taken my degree,</l>
                  <l>And Doctor <hi>Dun</hi> ſhould have preſented me;</l>
                  <l>There with an <hi>Hempen Hood</hi> ſhould be ſped;</l>
                  <l>And his <hi>thee-corner'd Cap</hi> ſhould crown my head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here I am come to hold up guilty hand,</l>
                  <l>And of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to give my ſelf the <hi>brand;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here by confeſſing I have been i'th wrong,</l>
                  <l>I come to <hi>bore</hi> my ſelf through my own <hi>tongue.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Learning my poor Parents brought up me,</l>
                  <l>And ſent me to the Univerſitie;</l>
                  <l>There I ſoon found <hi>bowing</hi> the way to <hi>riſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And th' only <hi>Logick</hi> was the <hi>Falacies.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſtead of <hi>Ariſtotles Organon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Anthems and Organs I did ſtudy on;</l>
                  <l>If I could play on them, I ſoon did find,</l>
                  <l>I rightly had Preferment in the <hi>wind.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I follow'd that hot ſcent without controul,</l>
                  <l>I bow'd my body, and I ſung <hi>Fa Sol;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I cozen'd Doctor <hi>Couzens,</hi> and ere long</l>
                  <l>A Fellow ſhip obtained for <hi>a Song.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60727:48"/>
                  <l>Then by degrees I climb'd, until I <hi>got</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Friends,</hi> good <hi>Cloaths,</hi> good <hi>Commons,</hi> and what not?</l>
                  <l>I <hi>got</hi> ſo long, until at length <hi>I got</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Wench with Child,</hi> and then I got a blot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before the <hi>Conſistory</hi> I was try'd,</l>
                  <l>Where like a Villain I both ſwore and ly'd</l>
                  <l>And from <hi>the whore I made</hi> I was <hi>made free,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By purging of my ſelf <hi>Incont'nent-LEE.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But as I ſcorn'd to father mine own Brat,</l>
                  <l>'Twas done to me as I had done with That;</l>
                  <l>The Doctors all, when Doctor I would be,</l>
                  <l>As a <hi>baſe ſon,</hi> refus'd to <hi>father</hi> me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With much ado, at length by art and cunning,</l>
                  <l>My Tears &amp; Vows prevail'd with <hi>Peter Gunning</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Me to adopt; and for his love and care,</l>
                  <l>I will devote my ſelf to <hi>Peter's Chair.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cambridge</hi> I left with grief and great diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>To ſeek my fortune in ſome other place;</l>
                  <l>And that I might the better ſave my ſtake,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I took an Order,</hi> and did <hi>Orders take.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Amongſt <hi>Conformiſts</hi> I my ſelf did liſt,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Son o'th Church</hi> as good as ever piſt.</l>
                  <l>But though I bow'd, and cring'd, &amp; croſt &amp; all,</l>
                  <l>I only got a Vicarage very ſmall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60727:49"/>
                  <l>Ere I was warm (and warm I ne're had bin</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a <hi>ſtarved hole</hi> as I was in)</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Fire</hi> upon the Church and Kingdom came,</l>
                  <l>Which I ſtraight helpt to blow into a <hi>flame.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Third Part.</head>
                  <l>MY Conſcience firſt, like <hi>Balaam's Aſſe,</hi> was ſhy,</l>
                  <l>Bogled and winc'd; which when I did eſpy,</l>
                  <l>I cudgeld her, and ſpur'd her on each ſide,</l>
                  <l>Until the Jade her paces all could ride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When firſt I mounted on her tender back,</l>
                  <l>She would not leave the <hi>Proteſtant dull Rack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till in her mouth the <hi>Cov'nant Bit</hi> I got</l>
                  <l>And made her learn the <hi>Presbyterian Trot;</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twas an hard Trot, and fretted her (alas)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Independent Amble</hi> eaſier was,</l>
                  <l>I taught her that, and out of that to fall</l>
                  <l>To the <hi>Tantivy</hi> of <hi>Prela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ical.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I rode her once to <hi>Rumford</hi> with a pack</l>
                  <l>Of Arguments for th' Cov'nant on her back.</l>
                  <l>That Journey ſhe perform'd at ſuch a rate,</l>
                  <l>Th 'Committee gave me a rich <hi>piece of Plate.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60727:49"/>
                  <l>From <hi>Hatfield to St. Albans</hi> I did ride,</l>
                  <l>The Army call'd for me to be their <hi>Guide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There I ſo ſpurd her, that I made her fling,</l>
                  <l>Not only <hi>dirt,</hi> but <hi>blood</hi> upon my <hi>King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Cromwel</hi> turn'd his Maſters out by force;</l>
                  <l>I made the Beaſt draw like a <hi>Brewers horſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Under the <hi>Rump</hi> I made her wear a <hi>Crooper,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And under <hi>Lambert</hi> ſhe became a <hi>Trooper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Noble <hi>Monk</hi> the KING did home conveigh,</l>
                  <l>She (like <hi>Darius</hi> Steed) began to <hi>neigh.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I taught her ſince to <hi>Organ Pipes</hi> to prance,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Banks</hi> his Horſe could to a <hi>Fiddle</hi> dance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now with a <hi>Snaffle,</hi> or a <hi>twined thread,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>any Government</hi> ſhe'l <hi>turn her head:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I have ſo <hi>broke</hi> her, ſhe doth never ſtart,</l>
                  <l>And that's the meaning of my <hi>broken heart:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have found out a cunning way with eaſe,</l>
                  <l>To make her <hi>caſt her Coat</hi> when ere I pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>And if at <hi>Rack</hi> and <hi>Manger</hi> ſhe may be,</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Colts tooth</hi> ſhe will keep moſt <hi>Wanton</hi>-LEE.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'l change as often as the <hi>Man</hi> i'th <hi>Moon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>[His frequent <hi>Changing</hi> makes him <hi>riſe ſo ſoon]</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To eat <hi>Church Plumb-broth</hi> e're it all be gone,</l>
                  <l>I'le have the <hi>Devil's ſpoon</hi> but I'le have One.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60727:50"/>
                  <l>For many years my Tongue did <hi>lick the Rump;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But when I ſaw a KING was turn'd up <hi>Trump,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I did reſolve ſtill in my hand to have</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One winning Card,</hi> although 'twere but a <hi>Knave.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If the <hi>Great Turk</hi> to <hi>England</hi> come, I can</l>
                  <l>Make <hi>Gospel</hi> truckle to the <hi>Alchoran;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if their <hi>Turkiſh Sabbaths</hi> ſhould take place,</l>
                  <l>I have in readineſs my <hi>Friday face.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If lock in Iron Cheſt (as we are told)</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Loadſtone</hi> their great <hi>Mahomet</hi> can hold:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Loadſtone</hi> of Preferment (I preſage)</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Mahomet</hi> may <hi>draw this Iron Age.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Congregation way</hi> beſt pleaſ'd my mind;</l>
                  <l>There were more <hi>Shees,</hi> and they moſt free and kind:</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Chamber practice</hi> I did better thrive,</l>
                  <l>Than all my <hi>Livings,</hi> though <hi>I skimmed five.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mine Eyes are open now my Sins to ſee,</l>
                  <l>With Tears I cry, <hi>Good People Pardon me;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> Pardon I do crave,</l>
                  <l>And hope my <hi>Mothers Bleſſing</hi> yet to have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My <hi>Cambridge</hi> ſins, my <hi>Bugden</hi> ſins are vile,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſins, my ſins in <hi>Ely-Iſle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Leiceſter</hi> ſins, my <hi>Hatfield</hi> ſins are many,</l>
                  <l>But my <hi>St. Albans</hi> ſins more red than any.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60727:50"/>
                  <l>To <hi>CHARLES the firſt</hi> I was a bloody foe,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh I do not ſerve the <hi>Second</hi> ſo:</l>
                  <l>The only way to make me leave that trick,</l>
                  <l>Is to beſtow on me a <hi>Biſhoprick.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Eve, and for his ſake</l>
                  <l>A Biſhoprick in <hi>Scotland</hi> I could take;</l>
                  <l>And though a <hi>Metropolitan</hi> there be,</l>
                  <l>I'de be as <hi>Sharp,</hi> and full as <hi>Arch</hi> as he.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now may this <hi>Sermon</hi> never be forgot,</l>
                  <l>Let others call't a <hi>Sermon,</hi> I a <hi>Plot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Plot that takes, if it believed be;</l>
                  <l>If not I ſhall repent <hi>Unfained-LEE.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I muſt deſire the <hi>Crack-fart</hi> of the Nation,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>rev'rance</hi> to <hi>let fly</hi> this <hi>Recantation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our Names ty'd tail to tail, make a <hi>ſweet</hi> change,</l>
                  <l>Mine only is <hi>Strange-Lee,</hi> and his <hi>Le-ſtrange.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60727:51"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>THE PORING DOCTOR, OR <hi>The Groſs miſtake of a Reverend Son of the Church, in bowing at the nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of</hi> Judas <hi>at</hi> St. Pauls, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember 5. 1663.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe <hi>Papiſts,</hi> God wot,</l>
                  <l>made a notable <hi>Plot</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Againſt the Church and the State;</l>
                  <l>Which ſome with good reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Call <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſcover'd ere 'twas too late.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe who before,</l>
                  <l>Had weltred in gore</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Proteſtant Martyrs</hi> ſlain,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd with one breath,</l>
                  <l>Of Hell beneath,</l>
                  <l>To blow up all by a <hi>Train</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60727:51"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Biſhops,</hi> good men,</l>
                  <l>Were in jeopardy then,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>Commons,</hi> the <hi>King;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For the <hi>Catholick Cauſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be made a <hi>Burnt Offring.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus ſwell'd with diſpight,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe darkneſs and night,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n cauſed the brood to miſcarry;</l>
                  <l>That day big with <hi>Thunder,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Held forth Mercies <hi>wonder,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And therefore kept <hi>Anniverſary.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You the preſent <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Brethren</hi> repair,</l>
                  <l>With the ſeveral <hi>Corporations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Pauls</hi> Church to <hi>pray,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſolemnize the <hi>Day</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſo ſeaſonably ſaved <hi>three Nations.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>good Doctor</hi>—</l>
                  <l>When he came before ye</l>
                  <l>The Sacred Goſpel to read,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Judas</hi> his name,</l>
                  <l>(O horrible ſhame!)</l>
                  <l>He <hi>bowed</hi> his Reverend head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60727:52"/>
                  <l>Some ſay that his <hi>fight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Poor man) is not right,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh that it be no worſe;</l>
                  <l>But others think <hi>he,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Judas</hi> bow'd th'<hi>knee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For love he bears to the <hi>Purſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His <hi>Worſhip</hi> made doubt,</l>
                  <l>Where the battel was fought,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Michael</hi> did prevail;</l>
                  <l>But to me it is clear,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>an hundred a year</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He'l bow to the <hi>Dragons Tail.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Twelve Spiritual Promotions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A head full of <hi>Notions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſtomach more ſharp than a <hi>Sythe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of <hi>Biſhopſgate</hi> there,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps did appear,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Cloaths were <hi>pawn'd</hi> for his <hi>Tythe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe things ſet before,</l>
                  <l>And ſome ſmall reaſons more,</l>
                  <l>His ſlender wit had overthrown,</l>
                  <l>Nor can he tell how,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>read, cring</hi> or <hi>bow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By any one's Book but his own.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60727:52"/>
                  <l>What then ſhall we ſay,</l>
                  <l>Can he <hi>Preach,</hi> can he <hi>Pray,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or put to <hi>rebuke</hi> the <hi>Gainſayer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who in reading the Word,</l>
                  <l>Diſcerns not our <hi>Lord</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From him that was his <hi>betrayer?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sure this <hi>doting Fool,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt once more to School</l>
                  <l>Before his return to the <hi>Altar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such another <hi>miſtake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May poſſibly make</l>
                  <l>His <hi>neck</hi> to deſerve a Silk <hi>H</hi>—</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:53"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:53"/>
            <div type="title_page">
               <p>THE FAIR QUARREL. By way of Letter, Between Mr. <hi>Wanley,</hi> a Son of the Church; and Dr. <hi>Wilde,</hi> a <hi>Nonconformist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Publiſhed in the Year, 1666.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>London,</hi> Reprinted in the year, 1668.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
               <pb facs="tcp:60727:54"/>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60727:54"/>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nathan Wanley <hi>to Dr.</hi> Wild, <hi>who was laid aſide for Nonconformity.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SO the bright Taper uſeleſs burns</l>
                     <l>To private and recluded Urns.</l>
                     <l>So Pearls themſelves to ſhels confine,</l>
                     <l>And Gems in the Seas bottom ſhine,</l>
                     <l>As thou my <hi>WILD</hi> while thou doſt lye</l>
                     <l>Huddled up in thy privacy,</l>
                     <l>And only now and then doſt ſend</l>
                     <l>A Letter to thy private Friend;</l>
                     <l>Take once again thy Lyre, and ſo</l>
                     <l>Let thy ſelected Numbers flow,</l>
                     <l>As when thy ſolemn Muſe did prove</l>
                     <l>To ſing the Funeral of Love;</l>
                     <l>Or, as when with the Trump of fame</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt ſound forth great <hi>George's</hi> name,</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a ſtrain, as might it be,</l>
                     <l>Did ſpeak thy ſelf as great as he.</l>
                     <l>For while great <hi>Cowley</hi> ſeeks the ſhade,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Denham's</hi> noble Wit's miſlaid;</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Davnant's</hi> weary Quill lies by,</l>
                     <l>And yeelds no more of <hi>Lumbardy;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60727:55"/>
                     <l>While the ſweet Virgin <hi>Muſes</hi> be</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Wild</hi> led int' a Nunnerie;</l>
                     <l>While thus <hi>Apollo's</hi> Prieſts retire,</l>
                     <l>The Females do begin t' aſpire,</l>
                     <l>Pretending they have found a flaw</l>
                     <l>In great <hi>Apollo's</hi> Salique Law;</l>
                     <l>Theſe graſp at Lawrel, only due</l>
                     <l>To ſuch as I have nam'd, and you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Wild <hi>to the Ingenious Mr.</hi> Wanley.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat jolly Shepherds voice is this</l>
                     <l>Would tempt me from my private bliſs,</l>
                     <l>After his Pipe to dance, while Thunder</l>
                     <l>Threatens to rend that Oak in ſunder,</l>
                     <l>Under whoſe boughs in fairer dayes</l>
                     <l>We ſate ſecure, and ſang the Praiſe</l>
                     <l>Of our great <hi>Pan,</hi> whoſe care did keep</l>
                     <l>The pleaſent Shepherds and their Sheep?</l>
                     <l>Is this a time with wanton ſtrains</l>
                     <l>To whiſtle forth the Nymphs and Swains</l>
                     <l>To ſport amd dance, while Wolf and Fox</l>
                     <l>Lye lurking to devour our Flocks,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Romes Sheep-ſtealers</hi> ready ſtand</l>
                     <l>To give them their <hi>red letters</hi> brand?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Doſt thou not know, my ſanguine Son,</l>
                     <l>What th' <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> have lately done?</l>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:60727:55"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>London</hi> hath ſent up ſuch a ſmoke;</l>
                     <l>As may the Angles voices choake,</l>
                     <l>And make tears big enough, to vent</l>
                     <l>ſears in a deluge, to lament</l>
                     <l>The <hi>raging fury</hi> of that <hi>Flame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But more of thoſe that <hi>made</hi> the ſame;</l>
                     <l>And when St. <hi>Paul</hi> has loſt his <hi>Qnire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Twere Sacriledge to touch my <hi>Lyre.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>None but a monſter <hi>Nero</hi> may</l>
                     <l>Over a <hi>burning City</hi> play.</l>
                     <l>Nor would I ſing, were I a <hi>Jew;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To pleaſe a <hi>Babyloniſh Crew.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now ſince the time for ſorrow cryes;</l>
                     <l>In this I freely temporize.</l>
                     <l>So the bright Starrs draw in their light;</l>
                     <l>When Clouds club for an ugly night.</l>
                     <l>So all the Birds of Muſick ſleep</l>
                     <l>On ſtormy dayes, and Silence keep.</l>
                     <l>So froſt-nipt Roſes droop and fall,</l>
                     <l>Perfuming their own funerall.</l>
                     <l>So you have ſeen a well-tun'd <hi>Lyre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Swelling it ſelf with grief and ire.</l>
                     <l>In gloomy air, each heart-broken ſtring</l>
                     <l>Its own laſt paſſing-bell doth ring.</l>
                     <l>So when <hi>Bellona's</hi> Trumpet ſounds,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>ſofter Muſes</hi> Muſick drownds.</l>
                     <l>Sir, by my many <hi>ſoes</hi> you know</l>
                     <l>My Poetry is but <hi>ſo ſo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But why doſt thou diſdain or fear,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Female</hi> brows ſhould Lawrel wear?</l>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:60727:56"/>
                     <l>Haſt thou forgot that Noble Tree</l>
                     <l>It ſelf was made out of a <hi>ſhee?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Muſes and the Graces all</l>
                     <l>We of the <hi>Female Gender</hi> call;</l>
                     <l>And ſo if you have not more care,</l>
                     <l>You'l find the <hi>Furies</hi> likewiſe are.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor would I have you wonder why</l>
                     <l>Our Poets <hi>all amort</hi> do lye,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Claret</hi> and <hi>Canary</hi> ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>The Wits will quickly hold their peace.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vintnars</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> fall together,</l>
                     <l>If once the <hi>lvey-Garland</hi> wither.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sweet <hi>Cowly</hi> thought (as well he might)</l>
                     <l>He ſhould hrve ſhin'd in <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſight;</l>
                     <l>But Clouds appear'd, and he that made</l>
                     <l>Account of <hi>Juno,</hi> found a ſhade;</l>
                     <l>And though on <hi>Davids Harp</hi> he plaid,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>evil Spirit</hi> can't be laid:</l>
                     <l>Therefore the Groves and Shades he loves,</l>
                     <l>And his own Secretary proves.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your next mans temples Lawrel ſcorns;</l>
                     <l>Since greater pride his brows adorns.</l>
                     <l>He to <hi>Pernaſs.</hi> bears no good will,</l>
                     <l>Becanſe it proves a <hi>horned hill.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The very thoughts whereof I dread</l>
                     <l>Will ne're be got out of his head.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gondebert's</hi> ſilent, ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe his Muſe ſings <hi>through the noſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>One ſyllable of which poor he</l>
                     <l>Did loſe by an <hi>Apocope.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:60727:56"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wild</hi> ſayes, kind <hi>Wanley</hi> you'r to blame</l>
                     <l>Amongſt theſe <hi>Swans</hi> his <hi>Gooſe</hi> to name,</l>
                     <l>Yea though his lucky <hi>gagling yaul</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Once help to ſave one <hi>Capital;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Love</hi> then made him fear</l>
                     <l>His <hi>neck,</hi> not <hi>brow,</hi> a Wreath ſhould wear.</l>
                     <l>Next he did one a Loyal ſtring</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Georgicks</hi> and his <hi>Carols</hi> ſing;</l>
                     <l>But now becauſe he cannot toot</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Organtunes,</hi> he's made a <hi>mute;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And though alive, condemn'd to death;</l>
                     <l>Therefore, <hi>dear Sir,</hi> in vain your breath;</l>
                     <l>Although perſum'd and hot does come,</l>
                     <l>To blow wind in a <hi>dead mans bumb;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet as a gteateful Legacy,</l>
                     <l>He leaves to thee his <hi>Nunnery,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not doubting but if need require</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt prove an <hi>able loving Fryar.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60727:57"/>
                  <head>2. Mr. <hi>Wanley</hi> to Dr. <hi>Wild.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat ſullen wary Shepherds voice is this,</l>
                     <l>That won't be tempted from his private bliſs,</l>
                     <l>But arbor'd up in <hi>Eglantine,</hi> while Thunder</l>
                     <l>Threatens to rend and rive that <hi>Oak</hi> in ſunder,</l>
                     <l>Under whoſe boughs himſelf in fairer dayes</l>
                     <l>Did ſit ſecure with us, and ſang the praiſe</l>
                     <l>Of that <hi>great Pan,</hi> whoſe watchful care did <hi>keep</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At once the pleaſant Shepherd and his Sheep?</l>
                     <l>Is this a time for Shepherds to retreat,</l>
                     <l>And ſeek out <hi>Coverts</hi> from the <hi>ſcorching heat?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is this a time for an <hi>inglorious ſloth</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To hug it ſelf, not daring to peep forth</l>
                     <l>Into the open field, while <hi>th' crafty Fox</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lurks in the buſhes to devour our <hi>Flocks,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Wolves</hi> of <hi>Romulus</hi> are grown ſo bold,</l>
                     <l>To fright the ſilly Sheep ev'n in their Fold?</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou not know what <hi>crops</hi> the <hi>Plauge</hi> his made</l>
                     <l>And, <hi>Sampſon</hi>-like, <hi>heaps upon heaps</hi> has laid?</l>
                     <l>That if Heav'ns wrathful Anger thus proceed,</l>
                     <l>There will no Flocks be left for thee to feed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>London</hi> has ſent up ſuch a darkning ſmoak,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall it too the Angels voices choak?</l>
                     <l>Shall it make Clouds ſo thick and dark, that we</l>
                     <l>Shall never more thy publick Cenſers ſee?</l>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:60727:57"/>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>Sacriledge</hi> to rob the Church; and thence</l>
                     <l>Since you have ſtole your ſelf, what's your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence?</l>
                     <l>When the <hi>white Harveſt</hi> for <hi>more Reapers</hi> cryes,</l>
                     <l>How canſt thou freely ſit and <hi>temporize?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So Stars reſerve themſelves for pitchy night,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> pouders all his locks with light.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>feral</hi> Birds delight to ſit alone,</l>
                     <l>Till the Days glories are packt up and gone.</l>
                     <l>So Roſes fall in <hi>June</hi> when froſts are paſt,</l>
                     <l>And on dull earth lye bluſhing out their laſt,</l>
                     <l>So the Muſitian ſmothers his <hi>Sol fa,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When he's entreated or to ſing or play.</l>
                     <l>So when the fierce <hi>Bellona's</hi> Drums do beat,</l>
                     <l>Who has no mind to fight, ſeeks his retreat.</l>
                     <l>And ſo I've ſeen a long miſwonted Lyre</l>
                     <l>Sigh its own Dirge with its own broken wire,</l>
                     <l>And ſeems to ſhiv'r at th' <hi>downfal</hi> of <hi>Paul's Quire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Say we not well, Agues will have their courſe?</l>
                     <l>Yes, yes, they muſt remember with remorſe</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Ivy Garland's</hi> withering, dearth of Liquer,</l>
                     <l>That would make <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> the quicker. But why ſhouldſt thou, kind ſoul, be in ſuch fear,</l>
                     <l>That plump <hi>Lyceus</hi> ſhould grow lean this year?</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou forgot how fatal the Grape-ſtone</l>
                     <l>Did whilom prove to poor <hi>Anacreon?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which of the <hi>Muſes</hi> or the <hi>Graces</hi> all,</l>
                     <l>Did ere for <hi>Claret</hi> or <hi>Canary</hi> call?</l>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:60727:58"/>
                     <l>Is it not ſung by the <hi>Venetian</hi> Swain,</l>
                     <l>How the brisk Wine gives <hi>Horns</hi> to the poor man?</l>
                     <l>And if you have no greater care, no doubt</l>
                     <l>You'l find the <hi>Claret</hi> will revive your <hi>Gout,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then we ſhall hear thy <hi>Gooſe-gagling</hi> yaul</l>
                     <l>Cry out for help to ſave thy <hi>Pedeſtal;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then we ſhall ſee thee, ſtanding on one foot,</l>
                     <l>Practiſe worſe tunes than <hi>Organs</hi> ever toot.</l>
                     <l>This is a vain preſage; thou ſay'ſt, the Dead</l>
                     <l>Have out-liv'd this, and have <hi>no Gout</hi> to dread.</l>
                     <l>But art thou dead indeed? Though dead thou art,</l>
                     <l>Heark how the <hi>dead mans bum</hi> does let a <hi>fart.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When as my baſhful Muſe did to thee come,</l>
                     <l>'Twas not ſo kindly done to turn thy <hi>bum;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To vote her of the <hi>Babyloniſh Crew;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſet the <hi>Furi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> on her with <hi>ha-loo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This 'tis to gad abroad, 'tis juſt upon her;</l>
                     <l>Had <hi>Dina</hi> kept at home, ſhee'd ſav'd her <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But I'm <hi>thy Son,</hi> and muſt corrected be;</l>
                     <l>But why then doſt thou turn thy <hi>bum</hi> to me?</l>
                     <l>Doſt think thy Son ſo <hi>ſanguine</hi> and <hi>inſano,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To probe thee with a Fiſtula in <hi>Ano.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This I ſhould leave to any of the <hi>Crew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You may believe me though I were a <hi>Jew.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And may my breath be ſtill perfum'd, why not?</l>
                     <l>Since dead Corps ſmell when they begin to rot.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60727:58"/>
                     <l>And he whoſe Muſe ſuch wondrous heights did fly,</l>
                     <l>That it did ſeem to top the very Sky;</l>
                     <l>And though he may have reaſon to be proud,</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of <hi>Juno</hi> did imbrace a Cloud;</l>
                     <l>May he reſume King <hi>Davids Harp</hi> and play</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Tarantul'</hi> of diſcontent away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If <hi>Denhams</hi> has ſo fouly bin betray'd,</l>
                     <l>And his <hi>Incloſure</hi> 'gainſt his will <hi>ſurvey'd:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May he recover all his Wits and more,</l>
                     <l>And with ſuch keen <hi>Iambricks</hi> brand the <hi>Whore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That all may dread it worſe then loſs of life,</l>
                     <l>To turn a Poet <hi>frantick</hi> for his <hi>Wife.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Poor <hi>Davenant's Noſe</hi> it ſeems is grown ſo ſore,</l>
                     <l>It ſcarcely will abide one ſmart Jeſt more.</l>
                     <l>Well may the <hi>bridge</hi> be down, when time doth meet</l>
                     <l>To preſs it with his <hi>Satyr</hi> cloven feet.</l>
                     <l>And thou with thy <hi>Apocopes</hi> art wont</l>
                     <l>To ſcater balls of thy <hi>Wild-fire</hi> upon't.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſhall I not, <hi>kind Wild,</hi> remember thee,</l>
                     <l>Who haſt bequeath'd me ſuch a <hi>Legacie?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis thine for life, we know thy ſubtile head;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wills</hi> have no force till the <hi>Teſtator's</hi> dead;</l>
                     <l>And that none can have ought by thy bequeſt</l>
                     <l>Till thou art better dead then in a Jeſt:</l>
                     <l>Nor would I that in tenderneſs to me</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhoulſt ſuſpect thine own ſufficiencie;</l>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60727:59"/>
                     <l>Enjoy it freely, ſince thou haſt it wed,</l>
                     <l>'Tis Inceſt to aſcend the Fathers bed.</l>
                     <l>What though thou ownſt me for thy <hi>ſanguine Child,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet I have not ſo much my <hi>Sire</hi> of <hi>Wild.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thus far is thy <hi>Fry'r</hi> able to ſee</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Covent's</hi> better than thy <hi>Nunnerie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He's <hi>loving</hi> too, 'tis true, he nothing gives,</l>
                     <l>As thou, at his deceaſe, but while he lives</l>
                     <l>All theſe <hi>good wiſhes,</hi> ſuch as he can ſpare.</l>
                     <l>And if thou haſt them, will help mend thy fare.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May</hi> every Knight about us, that's inclind,</l>
                     <l>Be unto thee, as Sir <hi>John Baber,</hi> kind.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ten</hi> Silver <hi>Crowns</hi> let each of them ſend thee,</l>
                     <l>And be ſo paid for all in <hi>Verſe</hi> as he.</l>
                     <l>May the <hi>poor Scholar</hi> ne're want <hi>Sunday Pudden,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When he's not like to <hi>preach</hi> for't <hi>on the ſudden.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May thy afflicted <hi>Toe</hi> ne're feel the <hi>Gout;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or if it muſt, let the <hi>Dutch</hi> have a <hi>Rout;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That thou maieſt yet (at laſt) once more Proteſt</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Recipe</hi> wants no <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Maiſt thou next ſend me what is worth thy Pen;</l>
                     <l>May I have brains to anſwer it agen.</l>
                     <l>May all that are of ſuch <hi>good wiſhes</hi> ſullen,</l>
                     <l>Live till their good Friends bury them in <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60727:59"/>
                  <head>Dr. <hi>Wild</hi> to Mr. <hi>Wanley.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOneſtly done however, though the Stuff</l>
                     <l>You ſent be <hi>courſe</hi> the meaſure's <hi>larg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> enough.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The firſt Cup thou beganſt I could not paſs,</l>
                     <l>The Wine was brisk, and in a little glaſs:</l>
                     <l>But now to pledge thee I am not inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>You <hi>Sons o'th Church</hi> are for <hi>large draughts</hi> I find.</l>
                     <l>Prithee leave off, for thou haſt been ſo free</l>
                     <l>In ſending ſuch a <hi>brimmer</hi> unto me,</l>
                     <l>That Sunday laſt, long of that frolick bout,</l>
                     <l>Thy Pariſh had but <hi>half a glaſs</hi> I doubt.</l>
                     <l>Beſides the drink <hi>is ſmall,</hi> you've chang'd your <hi>gill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I wiſh you'd kept in your <hi>hogs-head</hi> ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Yet, upon better thoughts, <hi>ſmall drink</hi> is fit</l>
                     <l>To cool the ſtomack, though not help the wit;</l>
                     <l>And that might be thy caſe: for certainly</l>
                     <l>Thoſe <hi>ſalt bits</hi> I had ſent thee <hi>made thee dry;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>ſick,</hi> which made thee drink <hi>ſmall drink,</hi> and ſtrain</l>
                     <l>To caſt them undigeſted up again.</l>
                     <l>Twelve lines return'd the very ſame, that I</l>
                     <l>Muſt call the <hi>Hickup,</hi> rather than <hi>Reply;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60727:60"/>
                     <l>Or, by rebounding of my words, I dread</l>
                     <l>There is ſome <hi>Eccho</hi> in thine <hi>empty head:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or rather thou my <hi>Cockril</hi> art, and ſo</l>
                     <l>The <hi>young one learneth of the old to crow.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay my brave Bird, thou dareſt ſpur and peck;</l>
                     <l>I wiſh that <hi>Shrovetide</hi> hazard not thy <hi>neck:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now prethee <hi>Chick</hi> beware, for though I find</l>
                     <l>That thou art <hi>right</hi> and of the <hi>fighting kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet thou art not my <hi>Match,</hi> and ſoon wilt feel</l>
                     <l>My Gout lies in my <hi>Toe,</hi> not in my <hi>Heel.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take this advice bofore you mean to fight,</l>
                     <l>Get your <hi>Comb cut,</hi> and leave your <hi>treading</hi> quite.</l>
                     <l>Thy Barber, or his Wife, if he ſhould fail,</l>
                     <l>Has skill to <hi>clip thy wings,</hi> and <hi>trim thy tayl;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thereby hangs another Tayl, I find</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>ſubtil noſe</hi> hath got my <hi>breech i'th' wind.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If thou canſt catch <hi>poor farts</hi> that Priſon break,</l>
                     <l>A notable <hi>Bumbayliff</hi> thou wilt make.</l>
                     <l>Hark, hark, ſaiſt thou, <hi>he let a fart!</hi> what though?</l>
                     <l>It breaths forth <hi>no Sedition,</hi> Sir, I trow;</l>
                     <l>Nor is there any Statute of our Nation</l>
                     <l>That ſayes, <hi>in five miles</hi> of a <hi>Corporation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If any <hi>Outed-man</hi> a Fart ſhould vent,</l>
                     <l>That you ſhould apprehend the <hi>Innocent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If you ſo ſoon could ſmell the <hi>Pouder-Plot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What had you ſaid if I had <hi>bullets</hi> ſhot?</l>
                     <l>Fye man! our <hi>mouths</hi> were ſtopped long ago,</l>
                     <l>And would you have us ſilent too <hi>below?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:60727:60"/>
                     <l>But I diſplaid <hi>my bum</hi> before <hi>thyne eyes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Unkindly</hi> thou ſaiſt, I ſay otherwiſe;</l>
                     <l>For there thou mightſt have thy <hi>reſemblance</hi> took,</l>
                     <l>Dead mens blind cheeks do very <hi>wanley</hi> look.</l>
                     <l>And For the <hi>crack</hi> it gave, that did but mind thee,</l>
                     <l>To ſtrive to leave <hi>a good report behind</hi> thee.</l>
                     <l>As for the <hi>gall</hi> which in your Ink appears,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>in our ſufferings we are Volunteers;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'le not ſay much, I have more wit than ſo,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis ſcurvy jesting with edg-tools</hi> I know:</l>
                     <l>But Sir, 'tis cruelty in you, <hi>to whip</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Brothers back</hi> which you did <hi>help to ſtrip.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet thus your Grandſire <hi>Levi</hi> did before,</l>
                     <l>Who <hi>kil'd thoſe,</hi> whom his <hi>Cov'nant had made ſore.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you know who they were that gave the blow,</l>
                     <l>And then cry'd, <hi>Propheſie who ſmote thee ſo?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We durſt not keep our Livings for our lives,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>they muſt needs go whom the Devil drives.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea <hi>but we left our Harveſt, left our Sheep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>would not work in one, north' other keep.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I anſwer. No great Harveſt yet appears,</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure your Churches hang but <hi>thin</hi> with ears.</l>
                     <l>And though the <hi>Foxes</hi> breed, what need you care,</l>
                     <l>When-as your Shepherds ſuch <hi>Fox-catchers</hi> are.</l>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:60727:61"/>
                     <l>For pardon, Sir, my ſerious ſoul now cryes,</l>
                     <l>Your knocking me did make this froth to riſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Once</hi> for my Age, Profeſſion and Degree,</l>
                     <l>To fool thus is enough, and <hi>Twice</hi> for thee.</l>
                     <l>Thus great Eſtates b'imprudent owners may,</l>
                     <l>When ſtak'd at Ticktack, ſoon be plaid away.</l>
                     <l>Let's wind this folly up in this laſt ſheet,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>friendly part,</hi> as we did <hi>friendly meet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet, to requite thy <hi>Legacy</hi> to me,</l>
                     <l>Accept this <hi>Litany</hi> I ſend to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May thy rich Parts with ſaving Grace be joyn'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As Diamonds in Rings of Gold enſhrin'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May he that made thy Stars, create a Sphear</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of heavenly frame of life, and fix them there;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May that blest Life credit</hi> Conformitie,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And make e'ven</hi> Puritans <hi>to honour thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Maiſt thou to Christ ſuch ſhore of Converts bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That he whoſe place thou fill'st, for joy may ſing.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May God love you, and you love God again;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And may theſe Prayers of mine not be in vain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:61"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ITer Boreale. p. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Tragedy of Mr.</hi> Chr. Love, <hi>late Miniſter of the Gospel, Acted upon Tower-hill,</hi> Aug. 22. 1651. p. 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Upon the much to be lamented Death, of the Reverend Mr.</hi> Vines. p. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To the Memory of Mr.</hi> Jer. Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. p. 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Upon the Death of ſo many Reverend Ministers of late.</hi> p. 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Elegie upon the Earl of</hi> Eſſex <hi>his Funeral.</hi> p. 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To the Father of a very virtuous Virgin deceaſed, who deſired an obſcure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:60727:62"/> to make an Elegie.</hi> p. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In memory of Mris</hi> E. T. p. 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Epitaph upon</hi> E. T. p. 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Upon the Learned Works of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divine, Mr.</hi> Edw. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds. p. 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Another.</hi> p. 45</item>
               <item>Aliud. ibid</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Epitaph for a Godly-mans Tomb,</hi> p. 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Epitaph for a Wicked-mans Tomb,</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter to a Friend.</hi> p. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alas poor Scholar, &amp;c.</hi> p. 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Norfolk <hi>and</hi> Wisbich <hi>Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fighting.</hi> p. 56</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Upon the Death of</hi> Dennis Bond, <hi>Eſq;</hi> p. 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Upon ſome Bottles of Sack and Claret,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60727:62"/> 
                  <hi>laid in Sand, and covered with a ſheet.</hi> p. 63</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Eſſay upon the late Victory obtained by his Royal Highneſs the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>againſt the Dutch,</hi> June 3. 1663. p. 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Grateful Nonconformiſt; <hi>or a Return of Thanks to Sir</hi> J. B. Kt. <hi>who ſent the Authour Ten Crowns</hi> p. 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Poem upon the Impriſonment of Mr</hi> Calamy <hi>in</hi> Newgate. p. 71</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On the Death of</hi> Mr. Calamy, <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> known to the Authour of a long tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> after.</hi> p. 73, 74</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Loyal Nonconformiſt, <hi>or an account what he dare ſwear, and what he dare not ſwear.</hi> p. 84</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Recantation of a</hi> Penitent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus;
<pb facs="tcp:60727:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>or</hi> the Changling: <hi>as it was acted with good applauſe in St.</hi> Maries <hi>in</hi> Cambridge, <hi>and St.</hi> Pauls <hi>in</hi> London: <hi>in three parts.</hi> p. 91, 93, 96.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Poring Doctor; <hi>or the groſs miſtake of a Reverend Son of the Church, in bowing at the name of</hi> Judas, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1663. <hi>at St.</hi> Pauls. p. 100</item>
               <item>The Fair Quarrel: <hi>by way of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, between</hi> Mr. Wanley, <hi>a Son of the Church, and Dr.</hi> Wild, <hi>a Nonconformiſt.</hi> 107</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60727:63"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
